<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The wayes and methods of Romes advancement, or, Whereby the Pope and his agents have endeavoured to propagate their doctrines discovered in two sermons preached on 5 Novem. 1671 / by Joshua Stopford ...</title>
            <author>Stopford, Joshua, 1636-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 197 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 77 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61685</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5745</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R791</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12625992</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12625992</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64645</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61685)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64645)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 336:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The wayes and methods of Romes advancement, or, Whereby the Pope and his agents have endeavoured to propagate their doctrines discovered in two sermons preached on 5 Novem. 1671 / by Joshua Stopford ...</title>
                  <author>Stopford, Joshua, 1636-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[York :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64645:1"/>
            <p>THE WAYES and Methods of Romes Advancement;</p>
            <p>OR Whereby the Pope and his Agents have endeavoured to Propagate their Doctrines.</p>
            <p>Diſcovered in two Sermons Preached on 5 <hi>Novem:</hi> 1671.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> JOSHUA STOPFORD, <hi>B. D. Rector of</hi> All-Saints <hi>in the City of</hi> Yorke.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1672.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:64645:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64645:2"/>
            <head>To <hi>Thomas Rokeby,</hi> and <hi>John Brook</hi> of the City of <hi>Yorke,</hi> Eſquires.</head>
            <p>IT has been none of the Devills mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt or unluckieſt Arts to infuſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices into mens mindes againſt <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian practiſe,</hi> by repreſenting it in the moſt frightfull and averting <hi>formes.</hi> He changes ſhapes with it, and as he transforms himſelf into an <hi>Angell of light,</hi> ſoe he doth this into one of darkneſſe, and makes it appeare a <hi>State</hi> of the moſt diſmall <hi>ſadneſſe</hi> and <hi>hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</hi> And how much more readie men are to take the <hi>Devil</hi> at his word, than <hi>Chriſt</hi> at his, who profeſſeth his <hi>Yoke eaſie,</hi> and his <hi>Burthen light;</hi> who ſaith, that the <hi>wayes of holyneſſe are wayes of pleaſantneſſe,</hi> appeares too fully in the ſtrong and generall antipathie thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:64645:3"/> have againſt Vertue, who never ſo much as tried it, but take up impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit and confuſed prejudices againſt it, and retain thoſe as faſt, as if they were the products of many yeares coſtly experiences. And tis too evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that theſe have taken the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>root</hi> in the richeſt <hi>Soil:</hi> they ſeem no where more to flouriſh, than among the <hi>Gentry,</hi> and perſons of <hi>Quality.</hi> It is the buſyneſſe of their lives to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue pleaſures; and yet when thoſe of the moſt refined and exquiſite ſort would run into their embraces, they grow coy, and cannot be courted to receive them.</p>
            <p>If one of a narrow fortune and mean extract attempt to convict them of this foule miſtake, by the moſt convincing arguments drawn from his own expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, they either think it inconſiſtent with their honour to lend him an eare, or (if they ſo far degrade themſelves as to hear him ſpeake) they preſently
<pb facs="tcp:64645:3"/> except againſt his Teſtimonie, as being an incompetent Judge.</p>
            <p>And if we <hi>Clergy-men</hi> tell them, that a holy life is ſo far from implying any thing of real trouble or uneaſyneſſe, that its onely an Art of refining and ſublimating their pleaſures, rendring them more guſtfull and exquiſite: That the duties of <hi>Religion</hi> are not <hi>Toils</hi> but <hi>Refreſhments,</hi> not <hi>Yokes</hi> but <hi>Crowns,</hi> ſuch as differ onely in ſize from thoſe Celeſtial ones to which they tend: That the pleaſures of piety are ſo raviſhing and attractive, that nothing but a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ignorance of them can be <hi>Amulet</hi> ſufficient againſt their <hi>Charmes;</hi> I ſay, though we tell them all this, and a great deal more; yet they quickly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, <hi>that out of intereſt and policie we can ſay no leſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Teſtimonies</hi> of theſe perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rejected, and their endeavours un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſfull, I cannot divine what other <hi>Medium</hi> remaines to worke this <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction,</hi> except the teſtimony of ſuch as
<pb facs="tcp:64645:4"/> are in equal degree with themſelves, who out of their own experience can tell them, that there are no ſuch plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures on this ſide heaven, as are to be found in converſing with God, and walking in his wayes. Here they would have no cauſe to wave their wonted <hi>Priviledge</hi> of being<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> tryed by their <hi>Peers,</hi> or to except againſt their judgment in the <hi>Caſe,</hi> who being plac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in equall circumſtances with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, muſt be ſuppoſed to underſtand their utmoſt Temptations to <hi>vice,</hi> from whence alone all the ſeeming difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and uneaſineſſes of <hi>vertue</hi> doe ariſe.</p>
            <p>Could I bring the <hi>Controverſie</hi> to this <hi>iſſue,</hi> I ſhould think of no other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <hi>(worthy Sirs)</hi> than your ſelves, who out of your own experiences are able to give ſuch pregnant proof, ſuch clear evidence of the ſweetneſſe of vertue, and pleaſantneſſe of piety, as would even force this ſorrowfull <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> from them, <hi>O how ſadly have we</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:64645:4"/> 
               <hi>been gull'd and Cheated by the mortal Enemy of Man-kind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Soe great and prodigious are your parts, ſo deep and profound your judgements, ſo extenſe and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive your knowledge, as would prevent all ſuſpicion of a <hi>miſtake.</hi> And ſo ſweet and pleaſant are your tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, ſo prudent and innocent your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portments, ſo winning and obliging your converſations as would remove all <hi>prejudices,</hi> which too often cauſe great truths to be ſleighted, and ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions to become abortive.</p>
            <p>Your <hi>works</hi> of Charity, <hi>acts</hi> of piety &amp;c. are a pleaſant ſubject, which I could with ſingular delight expatiate upon; but I know your <hi>modeſty</hi> will not allow it and that great <hi>Opinion,</hi> which all men have conceived of you, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it needleſſe.</p>
            <p>When I have begg'd your Pardon for the rudeneſſe of this <hi>Addreſſe,</hi> I ſhall conclude with this hearty wiſh.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64645:5"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>That God would bleſſe you with encreaſe of grace, length of dayes, and at laſt with fulneſſe of glory;</hi> which is, and ſhall be the fervent Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </salute>
               <signed>Your much obliged Friend, and Servant in all Chriſtian Offices. <hi>Joſhua Stopford.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64645:5"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THe following <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> appeares in <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> upon a juſt and honeſt deſign <hi>viz:</hi> to vindicate it ſelfe and the Author of it from the unjuſt aſperſions, and falſe accuſations caſt upon them by a generation of men, who make Lyes and Calumnies a Conſtituent part of their Religion. I confeſſe, if carnal intereſt, or a pious deſign to advance errour and profaneneſſe, were able to change the nature of things, to make vice vertue, an immoral act lawful, they might, nay they muſt be excuſed. For, though they made ſhipwrack of truth and Conſcience toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet they are not ſo far devoid of reaſon, nor can diſ-believe their ſenſes, as to imagine that others, who are <hi>Friends</hi> to truth, muſt be <hi>Enemies</hi> to morality; and conſequently that the Principles, and Practices of their Church, truly repreſented, can be grateful and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to them. Their <hi>Doctrines</hi> are ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory to thoſe of the Goſpell, and their <hi>Lives</hi> ſo palpably repugnant to the ſanctity which they profeſſe, that a perfect diſcovery of them is the
<pb facs="tcp:64645:6"/> moſt powerful argument againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> and enough to render all their attempts, to gain Proſelytes, unſuccesful. All their hopes and ſtrength lye in the ignorance and credulity of the Perſons they deal with; for if they meet with any, who have taken ſome pains to inform themſelves of the true ſtate of their Church, and cannot be ſatisfyed with an implicit faith, or take things upon truſt, they preſently give theſe over as untractable.</p>
            <p>Hence it is that a true repreſentation of that which they call the <hi>Catholick Religion,</hi> is moſt frightful to them; as being the moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual way to make that abhorr'd by men, which is ſo loathſome in the ſight of God. This I have attempted in the following diſcourſe: at which they grin and ſnarle, nay (to uſe <hi>Davids phraſe</hi> concerning his Enemies) <hi>they make a noiſe like Dogs, and go round about the City,</hi> yea and Country too. <hi>They belch out</hi> Lyes <hi>and</hi> Calumnies <hi>with their mouths, and ſwords are in their lips.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If their boiling paſſions were once cool'd, and the ſtorm lay'd, I would mildly and ſoberly aſke them, what is it they take ſo much offence at? Is it becauſe I have ſpoken the truth? This is the true reaſon, but they are (I cannot ſay
<pb facs="tcp:64645:6"/> aſham'd,) but affraid to confeſſe it; leaſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their deſign ſhould be defeated, And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (the things being ſo groſſe which I juſtly charge upon them) they are oblig'd to deny the charge, and reward me with their uſual titles of <hi>Lyar, Calumniator</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That this falſe accuſation might not gain cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit with Ingenious and Intelligent Perſons, I have not only produced the teſtimonies of their own great <hi>Doctors</hi> (which no <hi>Romaniſt</hi> beyond <hi>Seas</hi> dare except againſt: though perhaps here they will, if their <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Credit</hi> require) and named the <hi>Chapter</hi> and <hi>Page;</hi> but alſo menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd the ſeveral <hi>Editions</hi> of thoſe <hi>Authors</hi> (to remove all appearance or ſuſpition of a cheat) which I have made uſe of. And I challenge any <hi>Romaniſt</hi> (who ſhall think that I have wrong'd their Doctors, and intends ſomething, which muſt be called a <hi>Confutation)</hi> to give me the meeting in an amicable way; and if upon the Peruſal of theſe Authors (which ſhall be in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe) it appear to any Judicious Perſon, that I have departed from the literal ſenſe of their words, or expreſſe ſcope of the place: I doe by theſe preſents ſolemnly engage my ſelfe to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſede his pains of an <hi>Anſwer</hi> by a <hi>Publick Recantation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64645:7"/>
            <p> One thing (Gentle Reader) I have yet to acquaint thee with, that as time would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to deliver much of what I have here publiſhed, ſo neither the place to mention ſome paſſages in it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <pb facs="tcp:64645:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Catalogue of the principal Authors produced in the following Diſcourſe, with the</hi> Place <hi>where, and</hi> Time <hi>when they were Printed.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>Azorius Inſtitutiones Morales. Pariſ: 1601.</item>
               <item>Bellarmine de Scriptor: Eccleſ: Colon: 1613.</item>
               <item>Bellarm: diſput: Ingolſt: 1588.</item>
               <item>Baronius Annal: Antu: 1591. Colon: 1603.</item>
               <item>Cyprian. 1593. Eſpenceus in 1 Tim: Lutet: 1561.</item>
               <item>Coccius Theſaurus Catholicus. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon: 1600.</item>
               <item>Cambdens Elizab: London. 1630</item>
               <item>Chamier Panſtrat: Cathol: Gen: 1606.</item>
               <item>Driedo de Script: Eccleſ: Lovan: 1543.</item>
               <item>Claudius Eſpenceus in Tit: Pariſ: 1567.</item>
               <item>Expurgatory Index of Spain. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lm. 1601.</item>
               <item>Eſcobar Theologia Moralis Lugd: 1659.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:64645:8"/>
               <item> Eſtius in 4 Libr: Sentent: Pariſ: 1638.</item>
               <item>Fevardencius in Eſth: Colon: Agrip<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1595.</item>
               <item>Filliucius Quaeſtiones Morales Colon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Agrip: 1629.</item>
               <item>Jacobus Gretſerus de Jure et more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibend: Lib: mal: Ingolſt:</item>
               <item>Goldaſtus Imper: Rom: Francof. 1613.</item>
               <item>Gregor: de Ualentia Ingolſt: 1595.</item>
               <item>Judices librorum prohibit: et expurgat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Hiſpan: et Roman: Madriti 1667.</item>
               <item>King James his Works. Lond: 1616<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </item>
               <item>Leonardus Leſſius de Juſtitia et jure Lovan: 1605.</item>
               <item>Layman Theologia Moralis Antu. 1634.</item>
               <item>Longus Sum: Conciliorum. Pariſ: 1645.</item>
               <item>Morneys Myſtery of Iniquity. London 1612.</item>
               <item>Pet. du Moulin de Monarchia Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rali Pontifieis Romani Lond: 1614.</item>
               <item>Poſſevin. Appar: S: Uenet. Tom. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1603. Tom: 2. 1606.</item>
               <item>Martinus Polonns Chron: Antu: 157<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:64645:8"/>
               <item> Ribera in Apocal: Antu: 1593.</item>
               <item>Rivet. Cathol: Orthod: Lugd: Batau: 1630.</item>
               <item>Spondanus Epitome Baronii. Mogunt. 1614.</item>
               <item>Sr. Edw: Sands Europae Speculum. Lond: 1632.</item>
               <item>Stow. London 1631.</item>
               <item>Eman: Sa. Aphor: Pariſ: 1600.</item>
               <item>Sixtus Senenſis Biblotheca. S. Colon: Editio 3.</item>
               <item>Sanderus de Uiſibili Monar: Antu: 1578.</item>
               <item>Suarez defenſio. Fidei Cathol: Colon: Agrip: 1614.</item>
               <item>Tolet de Inſtruct: Sacerd: Romae. 1601.</item>
               <item>Tertullian Antu: 1584.</item>
               <item>Iacobus Auguſt: Thuanus Hyſter: Gen: 1620.</item>
               <item>Viegas in Apocal: Colon: Agrip: 1603.</item>
               <item>B P. Vſher Anſ: to a Ieſuite. Lond: 1631.</item>
               <item>Iohannes Wolfius Lect: Memor: Lav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingae. 1600.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:64645:9"/>
            <head>Errata</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>pag:</cell>
                     <cell>line</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>l. 2. read commanded</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>l. 3. read Arts.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>l. 26 read propagate. So p. 13. l. 3. 8. p. 17. l. 19. p. 32. l. 4.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>l. 22. read frequently.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>l. 14 read tranſubſtantiation.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>l. 1. read It is. l. 5. read Scholia's.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>l. ult read geſtatam.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>l. 2. r. circumgeſtation. marg: r. 370</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>29</cell>
                     <cell>l. 4. read and ſo</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>l. 9 read affirm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                     <cell>l. 15. read unparallel.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>43</cell>
                     <cell>l. 3. read Pilot,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>47</cell>
                     <cell>l. 13. read intenſionem.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>l. ult: after receive, inſert theſe words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſome ſignal mercy, when we are</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>55</cell>
                     <cell>l. 18. read poſitively.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>88</cell>
                     <cell>l. 14. read Eſpenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>89.</cell>
                     <cell>l. 8. read d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Moulin.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>l. 19. read Calendars.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>95,</cell>
                     <cell>l. 8. read Wonder.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>103.</cell>
                     <cell>l. 19. read frequently.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64645:9"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>8 <hi>Rev.</hi> 23. 24.</bibl>
               <q>And the light of a candle ſhall ſhine no more at all in thee, and the voice of the bridegroom and of the bride ſhall be heard no more at all in thee: for thy Merchants were the great men of the earth: for by thy ſorceries were all Nations decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. And in her was found the blood of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and of Saints, and of all that were ſlain upon the earth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Introduction wherein an account is given of this day's Eminent deliverance which muſt be carefully recorded, and thankfully acknowledged by us.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS amongſt the judgements which God executeth upon the earth there is a great and wide difference: ſome be ſuch as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64645:10"/> neither <hi>Fathers, nor fathers fathers have ſeen ſince the day that they were upon the earth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this day,</hi> 10 <hi>Ezod:</hi> 7: Some be ſuch, as the <hi>very hearing of them ſhall make both the eares to tingle</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. 12: Some be ſuch, as are <hi>without</hi> the leaſt <hi>mixture</hi> and allay of mercy 14 <hi>Rev.</hi> 10 So amongſt the mercies and ſalvations of God there is a difference; they are not all of one and the ſame ſize. Some be ſuch as reſemble the ſtarres of the firſt magnitude; others ſuch as are like the ſtarres of the ſecond and third magnitude. Some are ſuperlative and matchleſſe; farre above others in their luſtre and eminency. Theſe mercies are to be diligently obſerved, and exactly number'd by us: Of ſuch we are to keep as true a Regiſter as <hi>David</hi> did an Inventory of the Gold and Silver that he prepared for the Temple. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22: 14, The Iron and the Braſſe, which was without weight he number'd not: but the gold and ſilver he weighs, and ſets down the juſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Talents. So though we cannot reckon every bleſſing that comes from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, in regard they are without number, and without meaſure: yet ought we to be exact in recording the golden and ſilver mercies of God vouchſafed to us. And as we are to commemorate ſignal mercies and deliverances, ſo to tranſmit the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64645:10"/> of them to ſucceeding generations. See this both required and practiſed,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Required 17 <hi>Exod:</hi> 13, 14. Joſhua <hi>diſcomfitted Amalek, and his people with the edge of the ſword. And the Lord ſaid unto</hi> Moſes, <hi>write this for a memorial in a book.</hi> 78. Pſa: 5. <hi>For he eſtabliſhed a teſtimony in</hi> Jacob, <hi>and appointed a law in Iſrael, which he commaunded our Fathers: that they ſhould make them known to their children.</hi> And what is that? read v: 4. <hi>his ſtrength and his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful works.</hi> Once more 102. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 16. 18. <hi>When the Lord ſhall build up Zion, he ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in his glory. This ſhall be written for the generation to come, and the people which ſhall be created ſhall praiſe the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2, Practiſed and that ſeveral wayes. 1. Sometimes by appointing yearly Feaſts of remembrance 9 <hi>Eſth:</hi> 21, 22. <hi>To eſtabliſh this among them that they ſhould keep the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day of the moneth Adar, and the fifteenth day of the ſame yearly: As the day wherein the Jewes reſted from their enemies, and the moneth which was turned unto them from ſorrow to joy, &amp; from mourning into a good day: that they ſhould make them dayes of feaſting and joy.</hi> in comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of that ſignal deliverance which God had wrought for them. 2 By making Euchariſtical Songs, which they taught their children: as in 15 <hi>Exod:</hi> for the overthrow
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64645:11"/> of <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> in 5 <hi>Judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> for the defeat of <hi>Jabin</hi> and <hi>Siſera;</hi> in 1 <hi>Sam:</hi> 8. for the ſlaughter of <hi>Goliah.</hi> 3 By their ſignificant names which were ſometimes impoſed upon perſons, and ſometimes upon places. 1. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on perſons. This courſe <hi>Joſeph</hi> took to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate the memory of ſignal mercies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd on him in <hi>Egypt</hi> 41 <hi>Gen:</hi> 51, 52. He called the name of his firſt born <hi>Manaſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h; for God</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>hath made me forget all my toil, and all my Fathers houſe:</hi> And the name of the ſecond called he <hi>Ephraim; for God hath cauſed me to be fruitful in the land of my affliction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like was done afterwards by <hi>Moſes</hi> in reference unto what befel him in <hi>Midian</hi> 18 <hi>Exod:</hi> 3, 4. 2 Sometimes upon places. Thus <hi>Abraham,</hi> when his ſon <hi>Iſaac</hi> had eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and a ram been accepted in ſtead of him, called the name of that place <hi>Jeh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vah<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jireh, as it is ſaid to this day, in the mount of the Lord it ſhall be ſeen.</hi> 22 <hi>Gen:</hi> 13, 14. The like did Jacob when he ſaw the Angel of God 32 <hi>Gen:</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>And if eminent mercies and deliverances are to be recorded, and the memory of them tranſmitted to poſterity: ſurely then the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative and tranſcendent deliverance and ſalvation, which was given by God unto the whole Kingdome; as on this day from the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64645:11"/> Gun-Powder Plot, may justly challeng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> place in that Chronicle and Catalogue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mercies. <hi>This is a deliverance</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>upon the head of which may be truly written; ſuch as the preſent age may admire; ſuch as poſterity will ſcarce believe; ſuch as Hiſtory cannot par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel.</hi> What the Hiſtorian ſaith of that day wherein <hi>Scipio</hi> and <hi>Hanniball</hi> diſputed that long depending cauſe between <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Carthage</hi> in open field <hi>vizt;</hi> that the Roman Empire had not ſeen a greater day: The ſame may we ſay of this dayes ſalva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion; <hi>England</hi> never received a greater deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. And therefore ought the memory of it be dear unto every one, that would not ſo far gratifie the Papiſts, as by the forgetting of Gods goodneſſe to ſilence and bury th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s their wickedneſſe, which ſhould ſtand upon record to their eternal infamy. Let us look a little into the blackneſſe of the Conſpiracy which wants a name to expreſſe it, unleſſe we call it (as one doth) <hi>a Catholick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llany</hi> and you ſhall hereby beſt diſcerne the traſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendency of the deliverance. Was there ever any wickedneſſe in all the Ages that are paſt, which by the help of Hiſtory we may come to the knowledge of, that did equal this? This was a Plot wherein the flower of our Gentry, our whole Nobility, the Lords annointed, the royal ſeed, nay
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64645:12"/> Proteſtant Religion were all devoted to one ſtroke of deſtruction. And obſerve what inſtruments of cruelty they had prepared for this ſlaughter; ſuch as that not one of that Aſſembly could have fled from the fury of, though they had had the wings of Eagles: nor reſiſted the force of, though their fleſh had been as braſſe or their ſtrength as ſtones <hi>vizt:</hi> 36 Barrels of Gun-powder. Theſe were the inſtruments of their cruelty; ſuch as were never found in the habitations of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi.</hi> Let us further obſerve with what ſecrecy and ſucceſſe this bloody Plot was carried on. With what <hi>ſecrecy;</hi> none could be admitted to conſultation about the thing but thoſe that would by vowes and oaths, and Sacraments, and all that is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, binde themſelves more then once nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directly, nor indirectly, neither plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nor by circumſtance to diſcover the Plot. And with what <hi>ſucceſſe</hi> was this bloody de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign carried on! How did God for a time ſeem to ſmile upon their project and facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate their work, when providence offered them the con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eniency of a Cellar; whereas they thought that by ſtrength of hand, they muſt have digged a Vault to lay their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in! God himſelfe ſeem'd to take their part: and they who in 88 had ſworn that God was turn'd Lutheran, began now to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64645:12"/> hope that he was become a good Catholick a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Theſe particulars diſcover the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of this deliverance which we comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The cohaerence of the words with a brief expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GOd who at ſundry times, and in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers manners ſpake in time paſt unto the Fathers by the Prophets, hath in theſe laſt dayes ſpoken to us by his Son. 1 <hi>Heb:</hi> 1, 2. by whom not only the Goſpel of ſalvation is communicated unto us; but alſo the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of future events in this laſt age of the world. 1. <hi>Rev:</hi> 1. That many things in this Book are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> hard to be underſtood is acknowledged by all; and therefore much revelation is neceſſary to underſtand this Book of revelation. But though ſome things be dark and myſterious, yet other things are plain and obvious, even to the meaneſt capacity; particularly this prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie concerning Romes total and eternal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. That by Babylon, mentioned in the beginning of this Chapter, Rome is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, we have the ſuffrage of Antiquity. † <hi>Babylon was as a firſt Rome, and Rome is as a ſecond Babylon</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin de Civit. dei</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:64645:13"/> 
                  <hi>Lib:</hi> 18. cap. 2. And in the ſame Book cap. 22. he ſaith <hi>that Rome is built as another Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, and daughter of the former Babylon.</hi> And <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertull: adverſ: Marcion: lib:</hi> 3. <hi>cap:</hi> 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Babylon in St.</hi> John <hi>is the figure of Rome, as being like that, a great City, proud of its dominion, and a deſtroyer of the Saints of God.</hi> The Romaniſts ſay that Babylon here is to be taken <hi>figuratively</hi> not <hi>properly:</hi> ſo that it is not the old Chaldean, but the new myſtical Babylon that is here ſpoken of. Nay further they ſay, that by Babylon in this Chapter and elſe where in this prophecy Rome is to be underſtood: ſo <hi>A Lapide, Ribera, Viega &amp;c.</hi> Nay <hi>Bellarmin</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>de Rom: pont: lib:</hi> 2. <hi>cap:</hi> 2. <hi>p:</hi> 718.</note> produceth ſeveral Scriptures and Fathers to prove it: But then they adde, this was true of Rome when Ethnical, and not now when Papal; of Rome under the perſecuting Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, not of Rome under the Chriſtian Pope. That this is falſe appeareth. 1. St. <hi>John</hi> writeth a prophecy not a Hyſtory; he tells us what ſhould be, not what then was; therefore if St. <hi>John</hi> ſpake of Rome (which they confeſſe) it muſt neceſſarily follow that he ſpake of Rome as now it is, Not of Rome as then it was; of Rome Chriſtian, not of Rome Pagan. 2. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt is to be in the Temple of God, which was not true of the heathen Emperours, 3. Its ſuch a Babylon that for a while they were
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64645:13"/> lawfully in her; but when her corruptions did encreaſe, then they were commaunded to depart. 4. That St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeakes of Rome after the coming of Antichiſt is moſt clear from ſeveral paſſages both in this and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent chapters. But Antichriſt was not to come (ſay our Adverſaries) while Rome was Pagan, but after the diſſolution of the Roman Empire. 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 2. 8, <hi>And then ſhall that wicked be revealed.</hi> And when is that? <hi>When he that letteth ſhall be taken out of the way</hi> v: 7. And who is this, but the Emperours of Rome according to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Antiquity? <hi>Who ſhall be taken out of the way (ſaith</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>De reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect: carn: cap:</hi> 24. <hi>pag:</hi> 688.</note> Tertullian) <hi>but the Roman State? the diviſion of which among ten Kings ſhall bring in Antichriſt. After the decay of the Roman Empire</hi> Paul <hi>ſaith that Antichriſt ſhall appear.</hi> Ambroſe. To theſe I might add <hi>St. Chryſoſt: Theophilact.</hi> &amp;c. in 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 2. The <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>In.</hi> 17. <hi>Rev:</hi>
                  </note> Rhemiſts call the Roman Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours <hi>the figure of Antichriſt.</hi> And the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients give this reaſon for it; So long as the Roman Empire flouriſhed, Antithriſt could not appear: for there could not be two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Rulers of the ſame place at the ſame time.</p>
               <p>By which we may judge what was the opinion of the Fathers touching Antichriſts ſeat. That Rome ſhall be the principal ſeat
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64645:14"/> of Antichriſt is confeſſed by many of their own Doctors: ſo the Rhemiſts in 17 <hi>Rev:</hi> 5. Again they ſay <hi>that the ſcariet whore, and Beaſt, and Antichriſt are one and the ſame. in</hi> 13 <hi>Rev:</hi> 1. But Rome in the judgment of their great <hi>Bellarm:</hi> is the ſeat of the ſcarlet whore; therefore it muſt needs be the ſeat of Antichriſt. <hi>That Babylon which St.</hi> John <hi>deſcribes in the</hi> Revelat: <hi>is the ſeat and City</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">* <hi>de viſib: Monar: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſt; de Antichr:</hi> 38 <hi>p:</hi> 758.</note> 
                  <hi>of Antichriſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Sanders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I might to theſe arguments ſubjoin the confeſſion of their two great Jeſuites, <hi>Ribera</hi> and <hi>Viega. This muſt be underſtood of Rome,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">† <hi>Ribera: in:</hi> 14. <hi>Rev: num:</hi> 42. <hi>&amp;</hi> 57.</note> 
                  <hi>not only ſuch as ſhe was under the Emperours, but alſo ſuch as ſhe ſhall be in the latter dayes. That the name of Babylon muſt be referred to her, and not only to that Rome which ſerved</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">* <hi>Viega: in: cap:</hi> 17. <hi>com:</hi> 1. <hi>ſect:</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Idols, before ſhe received the faith of Chriſt, but alſo to that Rome, which ſhall be in the dayes of Antichriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In theſe words then we have a prophecy of the diſmal and final deſtruction of Rome Antichriſtian with the cauſes thereof, which are three. 1. Their Avarice and Luxury. 2. Their heretical and damnable doctrines. 3. Their bloody cruelty.</p>
               <p>1. Their Avarice and Luxury; For thy Merchants were the great men of the earth. This cannot be underſtood literally; for it were a weak reaſon, becauſe thy Merchants
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64645:14"/> are great men, therefore thou ſhalt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd: By Merchants therefore we muſt underſtand Romes Factors, the Popes In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgencers, and other Off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cers of his Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer. Theſe ſell curſed ſpiritual Wares, Pardons, Maſſes, Diriges, Trentals &amp;c. and make merchandize of mens ſouls, and flouriſh by this traffique like the Nobles and Peers of the earth. <hi>Theod: Nie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> tells us <note place="margin">† <hi>de Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt: lib:</hi> 1. <hi>cap:</hi> 68.</note> 
                  <hi>that out of one Country, and Province Pope</hi> Boniface 9. <hi>received above an hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Florens. His Officers went out poorly habited, and meanly mounted, but they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with their ſtately horſes and in great Pomp.</hi> And what vaſt ſummes of money did <hi>Tecelius,</hi> and his fellow Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencers rake together in Pope <hi>Leo</hi> 10. time, All things are ſet to ſale at Rome, the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Prieſts, the Altars, yea heaven and God himſelfe; as their Mantuan ſpeakes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venalia nobis Templa, ſacerdotes, altaria, ſacra, Coronae, Ignes, thura, preces, Caelum eſt venale, deuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. Their heretical and damnable doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, which are often compared to entic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and intoxicating Wines: <hi>by thy ſorceries were all Nations deceived.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Original word tranſlated, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries, properly ſignifieth poyſoning: but here (and in many other places of ſacred
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64645:15"/> Writ) it is to be taken in a larger ſenſe, and denotes the craft and ſubtilty, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods and Acts of inſinuation, by which the Pope and his Agents ſeduce the Nations to their damnable principles, and abominable practices.</p>
               <p>3. Their bloody cruelty: <hi>And in her was found the blood of Prophets, and of Saints, and of all that were ſlain upon the earth.</hi> But how can this be, ſince ſo many thouſands have been ſlain in other parts and places of the world? I anſwer, either becauſe the doctrine which cauſed their blood to be ſhed, was from Rome; or becauſe ſhe gave com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to ſlay the Saints and Servants of God who were barbarouſly murther'd and maſſacred in other Kingdomes and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trys, as <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> &amp;c. God plagues Rome as the Original cauſe of all this cruelty. But more of this afterwards<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The two latter cauſes of Romes deſtruction I intend to inſiſt upon; Hence we may note.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſer:</hi> That the wayes and methods which Rome Papal hath uſed to advance he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelfe, and propogate her doctrines wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bring inevitable ruine and deſtruction upon her. In the proſecution of this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinal propoſition I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll 1. Give you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> account of thoſe wayes and method<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:64645:15"/> which Rome Papal, that is the Pope and Agents have uſed to greaten themſelves, and propogate their doctrines. 2. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the truth of this Propoſition. 3. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to ſome practical Inferences.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I ſhall give you an account of thoſe wayes and Methods, which the Pope and his Agents have uſed to propogate their doctrines. And here I will mention five or ſix.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of Romiſh Forgeries.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>1. LEt us begin with their Forgeries, which are moſt notorious. How have they adopted falſe into the number, right, and authority of true Fathers? Our worthy Dr. <hi>James</hi> hath produced about 187 <hi>Treatiſes</hi> (to which I could add above an hundred more) which are not only <hi>ſuſpected,</hi> but plainly <hi>convicted</hi> of forgery by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts themſelves: and yet theſe very Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes are frequently urged by them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm their monſtrous Opinions. To make good this aſſertion, I will give you a few Inſtances: and here I ſhall confine my ſelf to their great <hi>Bellar:</hi> and <hi>Coccius</hi> whoſe wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings are ſo highly prized by all Papiſts.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64645:16"/> 1. <hi>Linus</hi> Biſhop of Rome his two Book<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>of the Paſſion of the bleſſed Apoſtles</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> Paul, are adjudged ſpurious by <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Baron: Tom:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>p:</hi> 785.</note> 
                  <hi>Baroniu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Poſſev: Appar: tom:</hi> 2. <hi>p:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>45.</note> 
                  <hi>Poſſevin.</hi> And though <hi>Bellarmin</hi> gran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that <hi>Linus</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it the Acts of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> yet he ſaith they are now loſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Clements eight Bookes of Apoſtolica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Conſtitutions</hi> are cenſured by <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar: de: ſcript: Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ: p:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</note> 
                  <hi>Baronius,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tom:</hi> 1. <hi>p:</hi> 145.</note> 
                  <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin</hi> and <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>de ſcript: Eccleſ: p:</hi> 58. 59.</note> 
                  <hi>Poſſevin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Clements Epiſtles to St. James</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are rejected by <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Apper: tom: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. p:</hi> 328.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmin</hi> and <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>de ſcript: Eccleſ: p:</hi> 56. 57.</note> 
                  <hi>Poſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the <hi>Areopagites Bookes of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Eccleſiaſtical and Celeſtial Hierarchy</hi> canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be his; for the Author of theſe Books (a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> appears by ſeveral paſſages in them) live<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apparat: tom:</hi> 1. <hi>p:</hi> 331. 336.</note> after the <hi>Nicaene</hi> Councel.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Origens Homilies upon Job</hi> are rejected as ſuppoſititious by <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>de ſcript. Eccleſ: p:</hi> 84.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellar:</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Appar: tom:</hi> 2. <hi>p:</hi> 526.</note> 
                  <hi>Poſſevin,</hi> and <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Biblioth: lib:</hi> 4. <hi>p:</hi> 285.</note> 
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Origens Treatiſes</hi> upon the 36, 37, 38<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Pſal:</hi> are queſtioned by <hi>Bellar:</hi> and reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Appar: tom:</hi> 2. <hi>p:</hi> 527.</note> 
                  <hi>Poſſevin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. St. <hi>Cyprians</hi> 12 <hi>Treatiſes de Cardinali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>de ſcript: Eccleſ:</hi> 84.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſti operibus</hi> are cenſured by <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>de ſcript: Eccleſ: p:</hi> 93.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and he gives ſeveral invincible reaſons for it.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64645:16"/> 8. <hi>Zeno's Sermons</hi> are accounted ſpurious by <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Biblioth: lib:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>p:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>13</note> 
                  <hi>Senenſis,</hi> and Cardinal <hi>Bellar:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>de ſcript: Eccleſ: p:</hi> 99.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Arnobius his Commentaries upon the Pſalmes</hi> are rejected by <hi>Bellar:</hi> and <hi>Sixtus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De ſcript: Eccleſ: p:</hi> 102.</note> 
                  <hi>Senenſis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Marcus</hi> Biſhop of Rome his <hi>Epiſtle unto Athanaſius</hi> is cenſured by <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Biblioth: lib:</hi> 4. <hi>p:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>05</note> 
                  <hi>Baronius.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>p:</hi> 396.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his Book <hi>de Imagine Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionis Chriſti</hi> is rejected by Card: <hi>Bellar:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De ſcript: Eccleſ: p:</hi> 116.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his Queſtions to <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De ſcript: Eccleſ: p:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 114.</note> are abſolutely condemned by <hi>Bellarm:</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Dorotheus</hi> his <hi>Synop: de vita Prophet: &amp; Deſcipul: Chriſti</hi> is rejected by <hi>Bellarm:</hi> as ſpurious and fabulou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his <hi>Commentaries</hi> upon the Epiſtle. of St. <hi>Paul</hi> are cenſured by Card: <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>de ſcript: Eccleſ: p:</hi> 143.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellar:</hi> for which he gives fower reaſons. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>de ſcript: Eccle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ: p:</hi> 153. <hi>Appar: tom:</hi> 1. <hi>p:</hi> 77.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Amphilochius</hi> his book of <hi>the life of St. Baſil</hi> is condemned by Card: <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tom:</hi> 1. <hi>p:</hi> 41<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellar:</hi> and <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>de ſcript: Eccleſ: p:</hi> 165.</note> 
                  <hi>Poſſevin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Athanaſius de Annuntiatione</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by Cardinal <hi>Baronius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. St. <hi>Hieromes Commentaries on the Epiſtles</hi> are cenſured by <hi>Bellarm:</hi> (who makes <hi>Pelagius</hi> the Heretick the Author of them) by <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Biblioth: lib:</hi> 4. <hi>p:</hi> 251.</note> 
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis,</hi> and <hi>Poſſevin.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Appor: tom:</hi> 2. <hi>p:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p n="18">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:64645:17"/> 18. St. <hi>Auſtines Queſtiones Veteris &amp; Novi Teſtam:</hi> are rejected by <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>De ſcript: Eccleſ: p:</hi> 187.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmin</hi> as written by ſome Heretick.</p>
               <p n="19">19. St. <hi>Chryſoſtomes Opus imperfectum in Mat:</hi> was written by ſome Arrian ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>De ſcript: Eccleſ: p:</hi> 176.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20. <hi>Cornelius</hi> his Epiſtle <hi>de tranſlation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Corporum P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tri &amp; Pauli.</hi> is rejected as ſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious by <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>De ſcript: Eccleſ: p:</hi> 89.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I might adde ſome hundreds more if time would permit: And yet theſe very Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes are confidently urged by <hi>Bellarm:</hi> and <hi>Coccius</hi> to prove <hi>Peters Supremacy</hi> (and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the Popes) <hi>Traſubſtantiation: Communion in one kind; Purgatory; Invocation of Saints</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I have obſerved above an <hi>hundred</hi> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, which paſſe under the names of ſeveral Fathers (who lived within 500 years after Chriſt) <hi>Cenſuredas ſuppoſititious</hi> by Cardinal <hi>Bellar: de Scriptoribus Eccleſiaſticis;</hi> and yet all or moſt of them are urged by him in his Controverſies againſt the Proteſtants. This is ſuch a piece of knavery, as none but a Frontleſſe Romaniſt can be guilty of. Forgery is a notorious Crime, and even in matters of leſſer conſequence ſeverely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by the Lawes of this Nation. <hi>If any perſon ſhall by falſe conſpiracy, ſubtilty, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>lt:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Eliz: cap:</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:64645:17"/> 
                  <hi>falſity, forge any deed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>harter, or writing or ſhall procure, publiſh, and ſhew forth in Evidence any ſuch falſe and forged deed, or Writing as true, knowing the ſame to be falſe and forged, and ſhall be thereof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, he ſhall be ſet upon the Pillory in ſome open Market Town; and there to have both his eares cut off, and alſo his Noſtrils to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it, and cut, and ſeared with an hot Iron, ſo as they may remain for a perpetual note or mark of his falſhood.</hi> Were this good &amp; wholeſome Law executed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Adverſaries of Rome (the moral equity of which extends unto them) they would have as <hi>few Eares</hi> as now they have <hi>true Fathers</hi> on their ſide. And ſo much concerning the firſt way and Method which the Pope and his Agents uſe to propogate their doctrines, by which mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes have been ſeduced.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>Wherein is declared how the Papiſts h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve corrupted the true Fathers, and ancient Writers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. LEt us now conſider their <hi>fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency</hi> in corrupting the true Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and primitive Writers. There
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64645:18"/> being many paſſages in the Fathers and other Ancient Writers frequently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by Proteſtants againſt them, to which they were not able to make any ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional reply; and finding that their nice diſtinctions, and ſubtile evaſions could not ſatisfy their Adverſaries, nor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out difficulty retain their Friends: they reſolved to eaſe themſelves of that <hi>Wit-labour</hi> for the future, and take ſome other courſe that might ſecure their delud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Profelytes, and <hi>convince</hi> (or at leaſt <hi>ſilence)</hi> their profeſſed Enemies. And what courſe more effectual to accompliſh their deſign, than by <hi>purging</hi> and <hi>blotting</hi> theſe <hi>offenſive paſſages</hi> out of the Fathers and other Primitive Writers? In order to this great undertaking the Pope ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed certain <hi>Cardinals</hi> with the Maſter of the ſacred Pallace general Inquiſitors at Rome; and to them gave he power to conſtitute particular Inquiſitors in every Dioceſſe. Hereupon they fell to work, and carefully compiled, and <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>I ſay pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately as appeareth by that clauſe of ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crecy in the King of</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ains' <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſion to the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. This Diploma or Commiſſion is Printed both in Dutch and Latine and pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ixt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgatory Index of</hi> Belg: <hi>and</hi> Madrid: <hi>in which the King af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms that he cauſed the Belgick Index to be printed by his own cheif printer, at his own charge not to be ſould publickly but pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately diſtributed to ſuch as ſhould be employ'd in the worke for their direction. And a litle after giving facultie to the Prelates to chooſe one or more Aſſiſtants, he adds that they ſhould keep the Expurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Index privately, and not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a Copy of it to any man.</hi>
                  </note> privately
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64645:18"/> Printed ſeveral <hi>Expurgatory Indices</hi> at <hi>Rome, Madrid, Naples, Lisbon</hi> &amp;c. wherein are expreſſed theſe ſcandalous paſſages (yet not the hundreth part of what they have expunged) in the Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Ancients, which are to be left out, when reprinted, which muſt be with all poſſible ſpeed. And to make all more ſure, they got as many of the former Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Fathers Works, as they could into their hands, not fearing their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries would reprint them, who wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted means to vent an Impreſſion, being prohibited to be ſould in all Catholick Countries.</p>
               <p>By this purgation they hoped that the mouth of Antiquity would be ſhut from uttering one ſyllable againſt them; and by inſerting words (for this they have alſo done) where neceſſity required, and by drawing into the Text of the Fathers the Marginal Notes, and Gloſſes of their Monks and Fryars, the mouth of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity would be opened for them.</p>
               <p>This villany is ſo notorious, that they endeavour to free themſelves from the imputation of it by a confident (or rather impudent) denyal of the fact.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:64645:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj:</hi> It it true (ſay they) that Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tors were appointed to purge Author<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but they medled not with the Text of the Fathers, but only with the Obſervations, Annotations, or Scholies that are made upon them by late Authors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ:</hi> The inſufficiency of this plea will appear by demonſtrating theſe three par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. 1. That they have command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeveral ſentences in the Text of the Fathers to be expung'd, and blotted out. 2. That they defend the juſtice and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of that Command. 3. That their practice hath correſponded with it.</p>
               <p>1. That they have commanded ſeveral words and ſentences in the Text of the Fathers, and other Primitive Writers to be expung'd and blotted out. This is clear from their <hi>Expurgatory Indices</hi> printed at <hi>Madrid, Rome,</hi> and other places. I will give you a few Inſtances, and ſo paſſe on to the next particular. In the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Index theſe words are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be thruſt out of the Text of St. <hi>Cyrills Commentaries</hi> upon <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> cap: 47. <note n="*" place="margin">Delea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtu illa verba: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> veró <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp;</note> 
                  <hi>Thou haſt proceeded ſo farre in impiety, that now there is left unto thee no place for ſalvation: for equal puniſhment will alwayes follow grievous offences.</hi> And upon 51
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64645:19"/> chap: theſe words: <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Delea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tur ex Tertu illa verb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Sed vbi non ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent &amp;. p:</hi> 62.</note> 
                  <hi>But when they caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all fear of God, and would not receive Jeſus Chriſt by faith, as it is written.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hillary</hi> in his Enarration upon 118 <hi>Pſ:</hi> muſt have theſe words daſhed out: <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Span: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex: p:</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> 
                  <hi>Non ex meritis ſalus,</hi> ſalvation is not of merit; with many other paſſages in his Works. I might inſtance in ſeveral other Fathers, which have many expreſſions againſt <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>try, Satisfactions,</hi> Peters <hi>Supremacy</hi> &amp;c. commanded to be blotted out in their Expurgatory Indices: but theſe are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to evidence the truth of this firſt particular <hi>viz:</hi> That they have command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeveral words, and ſentences in the Text of the Fathers to be expung'd and blotted out.</p>
               <p>Obj: <hi>Its true (ſay they) ſome words and ſentences are commanded to be expung'd out of the Text of the Fathers, but they are only ſuch as crept in either by the Printers negligence, or the fraud of Hereticks, that is, of Proteſtants. Concil: Trid: In In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice Lib: prohib: de Correct;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ:</hi> 1. The corruptions we charge them with cannot be attributed to the overſight of the Printer, or Corrector; for they are of a larger ſize: <hi>whole</hi> ſentence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are Commanded to be blotted out.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:64645:20"/>
               <p> 2. Nor could they be foiſted in by the fraud of Hereticks; for in thoſe dayes none of the Fathers had been printed by Proteſtants. Again, peruſe the places which we produce as razed and corrupted, and it will appear whether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ide, Papal or Proteſtant, were more likely to have an hand in it. The nature of moſt of the corruptions will diſcover the guilty per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>2. That they defend the juſtice and equity of that Command. Though their <hi>Gretſer</hi> deny this purgation of the Fathers. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de jure &amp; more prohib: lib: mal:</hi> cap: 9. p: 313—(where he chargeth <hi>Junius</hi> againſt whom he writes with a lye) and <hi>(lib:</hi> 2. cap: 7. pag: 298) calls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Dr. <hi>James</hi> to name but one Father purged, and corrupted by them: Yet he aſſerts the Popes Authority to do it, and and calls the exerciſe of it a worke of mercy. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. cap: 9. p: 321. And that he may not ſeem to contradict himſelfe in this and the precedent Chapters, he makes uſe of this ſubtile diſtinction: <hi>the Fathers may be conſidered either qua Fathers, or qua Fathers in law. The Fathers of the Church, as they are Fathers feed their Children with ſound and wholeſome doctrine,</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:64645:20"/> 
                  <hi>and are not to be purged: But as they are Fathers in law,</hi> that is, deliver any other doctrine than their Father the Pope, or Mother the Church doth or ſhall maintain, then they may, nay they muſt be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. cap: 10. p: 328.</p>
               <p>3. That their practice hath correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with that command. So much is acknowledged by <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> in his Epiſtle to Pope <hi>Pius</hi> 5. in which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his many and famous Acts, he recounts this for one of the greateſt. <hi>That he cauſed the Writings of all Catholick Authors, but eſpecially thoſe of the Antient Fathers, to be purged. Manutius</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd by the Pope to print ſeveral of the Fathers at Rome, ſaith, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>In praefat: ad Piu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>in lib: Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Poli de Concilio<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that care was taken to have them ſo corrected, that there ſhould be no ſpot which might infect the minds of the ſimple with the ſhew or l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>keneſs of falſe doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To make this yet more clear I will ſubjoyn a few Inſtances. St. <hi>Cyprian de bone patientiae</hi> tells us <hi>poſt guſtatam Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtiam</hi> &amp;c. After the eating of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt the hands are not, or ought not to be defiled with blood: But in their <hi>Cyprian</hi> printed at <hi>Colen,</hi> they have changed the words, and read it, <hi>poſt g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtiam:</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:64645:21"/> and ſo urge this place fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>circumgeſtation</hi> of the Sacrament. Thus much is confeſſed by <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Annot: in lib: de bone patient: p:</hi> 270.</note> 
                  <hi>Pamelius.</hi> That notorious corruption of St. <hi>Cyprian de Unitate Eceleſiae</hi> hath been often men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by our Divines. The Ancient <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, <hi>The reſt of the Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtles were equal to</hi> Peter <hi>both in honour and power.</hi> The <hi>Paris Cyprian</hi> hath added theſe words. <hi>The Primacy is given to</hi> Peter; <hi>he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed one Chair;</hi> Peters <hi>Chair. He who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh</hi> Peters <hi>Chair in which the Church was founded, doth he truſt himſelfe to be in the Church?</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Prefat: in I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rg: Belg:</note> 
                  <hi>Franciſcus Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius</hi> as an eye wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe tells us that being at <hi>Lyons,</hi> and inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately acquainted with <hi>Ludovicus Sauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> Corrector of the Preſſe, and going to viſit him he found him reviſing St. <hi>Ambroſe's</hi> Works, which <hi>Frelonius</hi> was then print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. After ſome diſcourſe <hi>Saurius</hi> ſhew'd him ſome printed leaves cancellated and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, ſaying, <hi>this is the firſt impreſſion which we printed according to the beſt C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pies; but two Franciſcans by command have blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out thoſe paſſages, and put theſe in their place (praeter omnem noſtrorum librorum fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem) to the great loſſe and trouble of Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonius.</hi> And not only particular Fathers, but alſo general Councels have been cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64645:21"/> and corrupted by them. The Councel of <hi>Laodic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a.</hi> Can: 35. ſaith; It is not lawful for Chriſtians to forſake the Church of God, and nominate or invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate <hi>Angelos,</hi> Angels: they have made it <hi>Angulos,</hi> Angles; that is, they muſt not forſake the Church and pray in Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. The Councel of <hi>Agatha</hi> Can: 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ſaith, Let no Clergy man preſume to ſue any man in a temporal Court without the leave of his Biſhop: But they read, Let no man preſume to ſue a <hi>Clerk before a temporal Judge without the Biſhop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> leave.</hi> I might alſo inſtance in the Councel of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> and many others: but theſe few may ſerve in ſtead of multitudes, which might be brought, of their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the witneſſes and ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing the Records of Antiquity, by which their Errors, and Novelties might be condemned.</p>
               <p>Many hundred, nay thouſand places in the Fathers, and Ancient Writers are purged, of which no mention is made in their Expurgatory Indices: ſo that now it is hard to find the <hi>Fathers</hi> in the <hi>Fathers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> of Rome have not only corrected and corrupted the printed Volumes, but alſo the <hi>Manuſcript</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:64645:22"/> Copies of the Fathers. I remember Dr. <hi>James</hi> of the Fathers in his Appendix to the Reader, tells us <hi>that in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>atican Library there are certain men maintained onely to write out the Acts of the Councells and Copies of the Fathers Works, who are brought up to imitate the ancient Letters: and thus Manuſcripts themſelves are purged by the Romaniſts.</hi> This information he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from an eye witneſſe. And this Story we have confirm'd in the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion preſented to the Noble Prince <hi>Henry</hi> to advance that glorious deſign which he had of erecting a Royal Library with all ſorts of Books, and Editions, in theſe words: <hi>The Pope gathereth up all the Manuſcripts he can into his Library the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>atican, and there uſeth them at his pleaſure. One of their tricks is notorious: they have men that can counterfeit any hand, and write the old hands that were written</hi> 500, <hi>and</hi> 1000 <hi>years ago: then they have an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial Inke, which within three dayes after the writing, looks as if it had been written</hi> 500 <hi>yeares before. Thus having altered, and taken out all that made for us, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, they ſuppreſs the old true Copies, and produce theſe now ones, as the Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall all Books.</hi> And doubtleſſe theſe are
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64645:22"/> the antient Manuſcripts, which <hi>Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> and others follow in their late Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Primitive Fathers.</p>
               <p>Neither have our Romaniſts content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves in corrupting the Fathers whether printed, or written, but they have proceeded to corrupt the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; which is a degree of wickedneſſe beyond all degrees of compariſon. I will inſtance in a few places.</p>
               <p>3 <hi>Gen:</hi> 15. <hi>And I will put enmity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thee and the woman, and between thy ſeed and her ſeed: it ſhall bruiſe thy head—</hi>The Vulgar Latine <hi>Ipſa centeret, She ſhall bruiſe thy head,</hi> that is the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s their Doctors expound i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. But the Hebr: Septuag: Chald: Paraph: Targ: Onkel: Hebr: Samarit: Syriack, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ick Verſions, read it either <hi>Ipſe,</hi> or <hi>Ipſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> And what uſe do they make of this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uption? To extoll the praiſes of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> and prove her patronage and protection.</p>
               <p>4 <hi>Gen:</hi> 13. <hi>And Cain ſaid unto the Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y puniſhment is greater then I can bear.</hi> The Vulgar Latine reads it, <hi>mine iniquity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> greater, quam ut veniam m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ear. then I an merit pardo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> contrary to the Hebr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g: Targ: Onkel: Syria: Arab: and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64645:23"/> Perſ: Verſions. And this is done to countenance their doctrine of merit <hi>de congruo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal:</hi> 99: 5. <hi>Exalt ye the Lord our God, and worſhip at his footſtool: for he is holy.</hi> The Vulgar Latine reads it <hi>Adorate ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellum pedum ejus, quia ſanctum eſt, adore his footſtool becauſe it is holy:</hi> Contrary to the Heb: Septuag: Chaldee paraphraſe &amp;c. And this place is urged by <hi>Bellar:</hi> for adoration of Saints <hi>De Sanct: Beatitud. lib:</hi> 1, <hi>cap:</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joh</hi> 14: 26. <hi>But the Comforter which is the Holy Ghoſt, whom tbe Father will ſend in my name, he ſhall teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, whatſoever I have ſaid unto you.</hi> The Vulgar Latine reads it, <hi>Spiritus ſanctus ſuggeret vobis o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nia quaec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> dixere: the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit will ſuggeſt to you all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever I ſhall ſay unto you.</hi> contrary to the Greek, Syr: Perſ: and Arab: Verſions. And what uſe do they make of this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption? To prove that whatſoever is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd in Councells, is to be received as the Oracles of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eph:</hi> 5: 32. <hi>This is a great miſtery (ſpeaking of Marriage)</hi> The Vulgar La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine reads it, <hi>Sacramentum hoc magnum,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:64645:23"/> 
                  <hi>this is a great Sacrament;</hi> Contrary to the Original word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is never uſed in Scripture for that which we properly call a Sacrament; and to the Syr: Arab: and Aethiop: Verſ: And this place thus corrupted they urge to prove that Matrimony is a Sacrament.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heb:</hi> 11: 21. <hi>Jacob worſhipped upon the top of his ſtaff.</hi> The Vulgar Latine reads it, <hi>adoravit faſtigium virgae ejus, he adored the top of his ſtaff.</hi> Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rary to the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, the Syn: Arab: and Aethiop: Verſ. And this place they urge for Image wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heb:</hi> 13: 16. <hi>With ſuch Sacrifices God is well pleaſed.</hi> The Vulgar Latine reads it, <hi>talibus hoſtiis promeretur Deut, by ſuch ſacrifices we merit of God:</hi> Contrary to the Original the Syr: Arab: and Aethiop: Verſ: And this place is urged to prove works of Charity to be Meritorious.</p>
               <p>Many more places both in the Old and New Teſtament might be produced, but theſe are ſufficient to convict the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Latine of notorious corruptions. Nay many of their own Doctors confeſſe as much.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:64645:24"/>
               <p>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtit: Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> lib:</hi> 8. <hi>cap:</hi> 3. <hi>p:</hi> 1155.</note> 
                  <hi>Azorius</hi> the Jeſuite ſaith, that many of their Writers ſince the Councel of Trent, <hi>Viega, Canus, Payna,</hi> and <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danus,</hi> have noted many Errors in the Vulgar Latine, not only by the fault of the Printer, but by the ignorance of the Interpreter.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Iſidore, Clarius, Brixianus</hi> (<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>This Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be expung'd by the Councell of Treat. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex lib: pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit: reg:</hi> 3</note> 
                  <hi>Praef:</hi> in <hi>Bibl:)</hi> affirmeth <hi>that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgar Latine is corrupted in</hi> 8000 <hi>places.</hi> And yet the Councel of Trent hath Conſtituted this the only Authentick Edition by which all Controverſies muſt be determined. <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t: Seſſio:</hi> 4. <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>:</hi> 21.</note> 
                  <hi>In all publick Lectures, Diſputations, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and Expoſitions this Edition muſt be uſed as Authentick, and let no man dare to reject it upon any pretext whatſoever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj:</hi> This Tranſlation is St. <hi>Jeromes,</hi> who lived in the fourth Century; and therefore not corrupted by Papiſts to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their Novel Doctrines.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ:</hi> Many Papiſts deny this to be St. <hi>Jeromes,</hi> and produce invincible Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments. Others ſay it is <hi>partly not wholy</hi> Jeromes: ſo <hi>Driedo.</hi> Some af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme (ſaith he) <hi>that this Latine Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Eccleſ Scriptur: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>b:</hi> 2. <hi>p:</hi> 40.</note>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:64645:24"/> 
                  <hi>is neither</hi> Jeromes, <hi>nor in all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the Original.</hi> And afterwards in his firſt Propoſition he ſaith, <hi>that this Latine Interpretation is neither altogether different from St.</hi> Jeromes, <hi>nor in all things agreeable to it.</hi> I will conclude this with the teſtimony of their great <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>De verbo dei lib:</hi> 2. <hi>cap:</hi> 11. <hi>p<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 120.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmin: The Vulgar Edition hath not one Author, but ſome things from</hi> Jerome, <hi>and ſome things from</hi> Lucian, <hi>and ſome things from</hi> Theodotion, <hi>and ſome things from another unknown Interpreter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo much concerning Romiſh For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries, and Corruptions; which give us juſt cauſe to ſuſpect the Antiquity of their Doctrines. For if the Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vote for them (as they would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the world) why do they produce ſo many counterfeit Treatiſes, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted paſſages, as lawful witneſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us? May we not well queſtion that mans title, who in Court produceth a forged, or corrupted Deed, when he knows his Adverſary is able to prove the Forgery?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:64645:25"/>
               <head>CHAP: V. <hi>Of Romiſh Treaſons and bloody Cruelties.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>3. WEE now proceed to the third Method which the Pope and his Factors have uſed to propogate their Doctrines <hi>vizt.</hi> their horrid Treaſons, and bloody Cruelties. The Romiſh Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors lay down theſe propolitions as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyable Maximes.</p>
               <p>1. That the Pope hath power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to depoſe Kings and to diſpoſe of their Kingdomes. For this they urge 1 <hi>Jer:</hi> 10. <hi>I have this day ſet thee over the Nations, and over the Kingdomes, to root out, and to pull down, and to deſtroys and to throw down to build, and to plant:</hi> which (ſay they) was prophetically ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Pope. And thus Pope <hi>Pius</hi> 5. in his Bull againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt: ad Micbael: Imp: Conſt: Baron: Tom:</hi> 10, <hi>p:</hi> 560.</note> 
                  <hi>Nicolus</hi> 1. proveth his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal power, becauſe it was ſaid to Peter, <hi>Kill and eat,</hi> and becauſe to him alone was granted that power to draw a <hi>Net full of fiſhes to Land.</hi> And <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Extravag: Tit:</hi> 8,: <hi>p</hi> 853.</note> 
                  <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8. prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Soveraignity, becauſe it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that <hi>in the beginning God creaeed Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth.</hi> But how weak, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64645:25"/> ſoever their proofs are, yet <hi>this</hi> doctrine is un animouſly received, and zealouſly defended by them. <hi>I</hi> could here produce a cloud of witneſſes, <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meron, Molina, Seulckenius, Coquam, Leſſius</hi> &amp;c. Theſe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th many others, tell us, <hi>that the Pope hath power to puniſh Kings by depoſing them, and giving their Kingdomes to others:</hi> That this is the opinion of all Divines both Ancient and Modern, of all Catholick Lawyers, of Occumenical Councels, and Popes: <hi>That in this there is no diſagreement amongſi them: That he cannot be held a Catholick, no nor Chriſtian, that is againſt it: That Chriſt had not been careful enough of the Church, and ſalvation of ſouls, if he had not left the Pope a power over Kings</hi> &amp;c. And that this is the judgment of our Engliſh Romaniſts is moſt evident from their numerous Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets; to which I might adde the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers of ſeveral Seminary Prieſts (when Priſoners in the Tower) unto certain Articles miniſtred unto them in the Year 158<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Nay they teach that not only the Pope but the people! alſo, may depoſe their Kings. And here let two of their great Doctors ſpeak for the reſt viz: <hi>Bellarmine</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:64645:26"/> and <hi>Eſtius.</hi> The firſt ſaith, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar: de Concil: lib:</hi> 2 <hi>c:</hi> 19. <hi>p:</hi> 139</note> 
                  <hi>That if the King turn Tyrant, the people may depoſe him, and chooſe another.</hi> And he gives this reaſon for it; <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar: de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>icis: lib:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3 <hi>c:</hi> 6.</note> It is the Conſent of the people that conſtitutes Kings, or other Ruler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> over them; and therefore if cauſe be giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, they may turn the Kingdome into an Ariſtocracy, Democracy &amp;c. And <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 4. <hi>lib: S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t: lib:</hi> 2. <hi>p:</hi> 444.</note> 
                  <hi>Eſtius</hi> ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe; <hi>The Nobles and people by the Authority reſiding in them, may defend themſelves from Tyranny and not only chooſe themſelves a lawful Prince, but alſo, cauſe being given, may dethrone him again</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And they mention ſeveral caſes, in which it is lawful to depoſe Kings. As <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>evarden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> 12. <hi>Con: in Eſt: p.</hi> 90 <hi>&amp;.</hi>
                  </note> 1. If they be Prodigal of the publick Revenues. 2. If violato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of the Publick faith. 3. If they be he guilty of Sacriledge. 4. If they be Tyrants. 5. If they be negligent, or inſufficient, or effeminate. 6. If they be Hereticks. In theſe, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſes, ſay their great Doctors, and ſome of their Councels, the Pope, and people may deprive King; and Princes of all Rule and government.</p>
               <p>2. That the Pope can abſolve Subjects from their Oathes of Allegiance, and their Obedience due to their reſpective
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64645:26"/> Princes. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin:</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Quaeſt:</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Art:</hi> 2.</note> Their Angelical Doctor tells us, <hi>that when any Prince is declared ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate for Apoſtacy, his Subjects are ipſo facto freed from his government, and their oath of fealty.</hi> And <hi>Franciſcus Suarez</hi> affirms, that the Pope can abſolve Subjects from their Oaths of <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Deſeaſ: Fidei Cath: lib:</hi> 3. <hi>cap:</hi> 23. <hi>n:</hi> 21. <hi>lib</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>c:</hi> 2. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>:</hi> 7. <hi>cap:</hi> 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2. 3</note> Allegiance; that to affirme the contrary is to act againſt the cuſtome of the Church, the uſe and approbation of General Councels, the Conſent of Catholick Doctors, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt reaſon, and is plainly Hereticall. And what was the judgement of Cardinal <hi>Perron</hi> is clear from his ſpeech to the third Eſtate of <hi>France</hi> (for which ſeveral Biſhops highly commended him, and the Pope gave him thanks) in which he ſaith, <hi>that ſubjects may be abſolved from their Oaths of Allegiance made to their Kings. That all parties of the Catholick Church did hold it, and ſo did the French Church ever ſince divinity was taught in Schools, till the coming of</hi> Calvin. Againſt this Speech our Learned King <hi>James</hi> writ his Remonſtrance for the Right of Kings, and the Independency of their Crowns.</p>
               <p>3. That Kings excommunicated, and depoſ'd may be lawfully kill'd by their
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64645:27"/> own Subjects; becauſe then they ceaſe to be Kings. <hi>Leſſius</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>: C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th: lib:</hi> 6. <hi>cap:</hi> 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 18. 14.</note> tells us, <hi>that the people, Parliament, or any other having</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtit: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 2. <hi>cap: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>:</hi> 4, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 12. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtit: lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Quaeſt:</hi> 1. <hi>Art:</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Authority, may depoſe a tyrannical Prince, and declare him an Enemy; whereby any thing may be attempted againſt his perſon, becauſe he then ceaſeth to be a King.</hi> Dom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inicus Soto <hi>ſaith, that when once a decree is g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne out againſt a King, then any one may be the Executioner.</hi> And <hi>Suarez</hi> affirms no leſſe then three times in one Paragraph, <hi>that Kings may be murther'd by their own Subjects;</hi> and he gives this weighty reaſon: <hi>When a King is depoſed, he is no lawful King, and therefore may be be kill'd by any private man.</hi> And that this is not the private Opinion of <hi>Suarez,</hi> but unanimouſly received by all Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, is clear from the high cenſures of approbation in the beginning of his Book. <hi>Alpho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſo a Caſtello Branco</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimbria</hi> declare: <hi>that he hath read it exactly over, and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all things in it agreeable to the holy Scriptures, Apoſtolical Tradition, General Councels, and Papal decrees. Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ando M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtin: Maſca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gnus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sylvis</hi> ſaith, that he hath alſo read it over, and find<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nothing in it, but what <hi>is Orthodox.</hi> And <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rte Alph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:64645:27"/> 
                  <hi>Mello</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lamego</hi> ſaith alſo, that he hath read it over, and thinks it <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be publiſhed for the publick good of Chriſtendome.</hi> Nor is this all, but (to paſſe over the Inquiſition, and others, who allow it the ſame priviledges) the Univerſity of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mplut:</hi> after a ſerious view, and conſideration of it, declare that there is nothing in it <hi>contrary</hi> to the Roman Catholick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith: that every thing i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>worthy of praiſe</hi> and commendation.</p>
               <p>Nay this King-killing is not only law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, <note place="margin">* <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> lib:</hi> 96. <hi>p:</hi> 454. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> but highly commended, and rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with eternal glory. They encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged Fryar <hi>Climent</hi> to murther <hi>Henry</hi> 3. <note place="margin">† <hi>Ant: Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>et<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p:</hi> 403 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> of <hi>France,</hi> with theſe promiſes. <hi>That he ſhall be well recompenced for the fact; if he dye he ſhall ſurely fly to heaven as a Saint, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll'd amongſt the Roman Martyrs on Earth.</hi> And this horrid fact was highly commended by the Pope in a full Conſiſtory at Rome. How did Pope <note place="margin">† <hi>Baron: tom:</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Adrian</hi> 2. extoll and magnify <hi>Baſilius</hi> for murthering <hi>Michael</hi> Emperour of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople? Party</hi> was confirm'd in his reſolutions to kill o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Q: <hi>Elizabeth</hi> by a Letter from Cardinal <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>o,</hi> in which we have theſe expreſſions: <hi>His Holyneſſe granteth unto you his bleſſing, Plenary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence,</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:64645:28"/> 
                  <hi>and remiſſion of all your ſins ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your deſire.</hi> And how was <hi>Barriere</hi> encouraged to murther <hi>Henry</hi> 4. of <hi>France</hi> with theſe words, <hi>that he ſhould gain by that Act, both great glory and Paradiſe.</hi> I could inſtance in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but theſe are ſufficient.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee what trayterous poſitions, and deſtructive of all Government, are laid down, and defended by our Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts. Our King <hi>James</hi> therefore had good reaſon to ſay <hi>that none of thoſe that truly know, and</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Speech in Parliment</hi> 1605.</note> 
                  <hi>believe the whole grounds, and School Concluſions of their doctrines, can either prove good Chriſtians, or good Subjects.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have heard what treaſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines are delivered and defended by our Adverſaries of Rome, and that their practices have been conformable to them all Hyſtories declare. How many trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have the Popes of Rome Committed, Commanded, and Commended? <note n="†" place="margin">Morneys Myſt: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquit: who ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Hyſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s.</note> Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> 4. and his Biſhops promoted the Rebellion of the three Sons of <hi>Ludovicus Pius;</hi> and <hi>Gregory</hi> 7. raiſed a rebellion
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64645:28"/> 
                  <hi>Henry</hi> 4. Emperour of <hi>Germany:</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gold aſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Imperii Rom Mon, p:</hi> 561.</note> 
                  <hi>Boniface</hi> 8. ſtirr'd up the people of <hi>France</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt <hi>Philip</hi> 4. ſirnamed <hi>le Bell.</hi> When <hi>Henry Bullenbrook</hi> Duke of <hi>Hereford</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter</hi> landed in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> moſt <note place="margin">† <hi>Stow: p.</hi> 320.</note> of the Biſhops flocked to him, traiter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly owning him for their Soveraign; and <hi>Thomas Arundell</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> Preached againſt <hi>Richard</hi> 2. then King, and produced a Bull from Rome promiſing remiſſion of ſins to all thoſe who ſhould aid the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt King <hi>Richard,</hi> who was afterwards murder'd in <hi>Pontefract</hi> Caſtle. How were the Iriſh encouraged to rebell by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> 13. his Breve, promiſing to grant them as plenary a pardon of all their ſins, as was formerly given to thoſe, who fought againſt the Turks? and was not the Spaniſh Invaſion <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cambden p.</hi> 128 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> promoted by the Pope, and our Engliſh Romaniſts? And that our late Warres here in <hi>England</hi> were raiſed and foſtered by the arts of the Court of Rome, is more than probable. <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Prot: Relig: p:</hi> 58 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> The Roman Prieſt and Confeſſor is known (ſaith Dr. <hi>De Moulin)</hi> who when he ſaw <q>the fatal ſtroke given to our late gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious King, flouriſhed with his ſword, and ſaid, <hi>Now the greateſt Enemy we</hi>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:64645:29"/> 
                     <hi>have in the world is gone.</hi> When the Newes of that horrible execution came to <hi>Roan</hi> (ſaith the ſame Author) a Proteſtant Gentleman of Good Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit was preſent in a great Company of Jeſuited Perſons: where after great expreſſions of joy, the graveſt of the company, to whom all gave ear, ſpake much after this ſort. The King of <note place="margin">A <hi>notorious ye</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>England</hi> at his Marriage had promiſed the re-eſtabliſhing of the Catholick Religion: and when he delayed to fulfil his promiſe, we ſummoned him from time to time to performe it? We came ſo farre as to tell him, that if he would not do it, we ſhould be forced to take thoſe courſes which would bring him to his deſtruction. We have giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en him lawful warning, and when no warning would ſerve, we have kept our word to him, ſince he would not keep his word to us.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That grave Rabbies ſentence agreeth with <q>this certain intelligence which ſhall be juſtifyed whenſoever Authority ſhall require it: That the year be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Kings death, a ſelect number of Jeſuits were ſent from their whole party in <hi>England;</hi> firſt to <hi>Paris,</hi> to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64645:29"/> conſult with the Faculty of <hi>Sor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>en;</hi> to whom they put this Queſtion in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: <hi>That being the State of</hi> England <hi>was in likely poſture to change Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether it was lawful for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks to work that change, for the advancing and ſecuring of the Catholick cauſe in</hi> England, <hi>by making away the King, whom there was no likelyhood to turn from his h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>reſy?</hi> Which was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered affirmatively. After this the ſame perſons went to Rome, where the ſame Queſtion being propounded and debated, it was concluded by the Pope and his Council, <hi>that it was both lawful and expedient for the Catholicks to promote that alteration of State.</hi>
                  </q> And what followed is known to all the world. Much more to this purpoſe you may read in the following pages.</p>
               <p>Time would fail me ſhould I recount all the Treaſons which the Pope and his Agents have been the Authors and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menters of. And yet theſe men (who make rebellion an Article of their faith) have the impudenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to ſpeak and write of their Loyalty to temporal Kings and Princes. Out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h Romaniſts drew up a ſupplication to King <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:64645:30"/> Parliament, in which they doe not a little vaunt and brag of the Loyalty of their Religion in theſe words: <hi>The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Subject is (if any other) the glory,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>pag:</hi> 7.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtrength, and perpetuity of the Kingdome, becauſe he principally ſeeketh Heaven in this world (and will not for the world be diverted) cannot be treacherous, or diſloyal, or undu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull to your Highneſſe, but in every ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and diſtreſſe occurring, valiant, reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, and moſt faithfull.</hi> And all theſe fair words were to the ſame King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, whoſe deſtruction they intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and had at that time contrived. O unparrallel Hypocriſie!</p>
               <p>And <hi>Philanax Anglicus</hi> (a late Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phleter) tells us, that the Romaniſts are <note place="margin">
                     <hi>pag:</hi> 104.</note> 
                  <hi>to fight onely with prayers; Arms againſt Princes have no warrant. Who is Judge if the King tranſgreſſeth the Conditions of his Kingdom? onely God. Navar, Cunerus,</hi> and all the Catholick Doctors that ever I have ſeen, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Surely then he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw</hi> Aquinas, Saurez, Leſſius &amp;c,</note> agree perfectly in this ſame ſentence. And ſo much concerning their trayterous Doctrines, and rebellious practices, by which the Pope and his Agents have endeavoured to propogate their Religion.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:64645:30"/>
               <p> Let us now take a ſurvey of their bloody cruelties. And here I muſt lead you into <hi>Golgotha,</hi> a field very ample and large, like that to which God brought the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 37. We may boldly affirme that the ten perſecutions of the Emperours of Rome, never put to death ſo many, nor with that cruelty, as the power of the Biſhop of Rome. Inſtruments of cruelty are in their habitations. To ſpeak of the Murthers Maſſacres and cruelties of the Papiſts is ſo large a field, that entering into it. I know not where to begin, nor where to end. I could ſhew you a Sea of blood flowing from the See of Rome: like to that which <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſpeakes of 47 chapt: 3, 4, 5. which was at the firſt to the Ancles, then to the knees, then to the Loynes, deeper and deeper. I could entertain you with a lamentable Story (which would make you abhor the very name of Popery) of their <hi>barbarous</hi> cruelties exerciſed upon the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> and <hi>Waldenſes:</hi> and their <hi>Pariſian</hi> Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre take briefly thus. <hi>Charles</hi> 9. King of <hi>France,</hi> under the pretence of the grand Solemnities of the King of <hi>Navar's</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with his Siſter, invited all the Grandees of the <hi>Hugonots</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> with
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:64645:31"/> 
                  <hi>Leiceſter</hi> and <hi>Burghley</hi> out of <hi>England,</hi> and the Sons of the Palatine Elector out of <hi>Germany;</hi> intending by this means to <note place="margin">* <hi>Thuanus lib:</hi> 52. 53.</note> ruine the Proteſtant Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gion. The French obey'd, and appear to, where they <note place="margin">† <hi>Camdent Eliz: p:</hi> 50.</note> were entertain'd with all manner of Gayeties and Triumphs: but the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was tragicall; for within a few hours many thouſands were moſt barbarouſly maſſacred. This cruelty was celebrated by the Romaniſts in <hi>France,</hi> as one of the moſt glorious actions the world hath been acquainted with: great rejoycings at Court for it, and publick thanks given unto God. But the greateſt joy was at Rome: Cardinal <hi>Lorain</hi> gave the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that brought the Newes of it, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crownes: the Letter was read in the Conclave; publick thanks were given in their Churches, the Cannons diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, Bonefires made, a Jubilee pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed throughout all Chriſtendome: And a grand Proceſſion was made to the Church of St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> where was the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, Biſhops, Cardinals, ſeveral Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, and the Pope under a Canopy. And the better to perpetuate the memory of this Maſſacre, the Pope cauſ'd it to be
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64645:31"/> painted about his great Hall in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran, and there recorded in Marble.</p>
               <p>I will not be your Pilat to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ft you into the Indies, where the Chriſtian Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts have kill'd more Pagans, then ever Pagans killed Chriſtians; nor yet ſpeak of their butcheries in the late Iriſh Rebellion. One obſerves that nyne hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand Proteſtants were murdered in Chriſtendome in a few years. And ſo much for the third particular.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Sect: I. Wherein is declared the ſuitableneſſe of Popiſh doctrines to mens carnal inclinations.</head>
                  <p>4. WEe come now to diſcourſe of the fourth Method which the Pope and his Agents have uſ'd to propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate their Religion, and that is, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodating their Doctrines to mens ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral humours and carnall inclinations. And of all their Wiles and Stratagems I look upon this as the moſt effectual: by their other Methods they have gain'd their thouſands, but by this their ten thouſands, This brings whole ſhoall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of ſilly ſouls in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:64645:32"/> their Net. Their Doctrines, and the reaſons of which they make uſe to ſupport them are ſo many means and expedients proper to authorize Vice, to ſupport ſin, to excuſe the moſt criminal actions, and to encourage looſneſſe and diſorders in all ſorts of profeſſions. What St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith of the whole Scripture <hi>viz:</hi> that it is <hi>Charity,</hi> and relates thereto, as to its end: we may ſay of Popiſh Doctrines, they are nothing but <hi>debauchery,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late thereto as unto their end. There are few Commands, either affirmative or negative, which their great Caſuiſts (the Guides of conſciences) do not free men from the obligation of, either wholy or in part, by the propoſitions they lay down as undenyable Maximes. The truth of this will appear by an Induction of particulars.</p>
                  <p>1. <hi>God commands us to love him with all our hearts and ſouls,</hi> ſincerely and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlatively. 22 <hi>Mat:</hi> 37. But from the rigour and ſeverity of this Law we are freed by the Maximes of their Caſuiſts, the truth of which we muſt not queſtion. <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Theol: Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral: Tom:</hi> 2. <hi>tract:</hi> 22. <hi>cap:</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>p:</hi> 48.</note> 
                     <hi>Filliutius</hi> explicating how we are obliged to love God, ſaith, <hi>that this ought not to be extended in ſuch a manner, as that we</hi>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:64645:32"/> 
                     <hi>muſt have in our hearts a more intenſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of love for God than for the creatures: and</hi> obſerve his reaſon, <hi>by this way</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we better provide for the peace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of pious perſons, who without this would be alwayes in doubt of their loue to God, if it ought to be in an higher degree than the love of any Creature whatſoever. And he brings in Aquiras, Valentia,</hi> and <hi>Azorius</hi> voting with him. And to the ſame purpoſe ſpeaks <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Inſtr: Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerd: lib:</hi> 4. <hi>p:</hi> 544.</note> Card: <hi>Tolet: We are not obliged</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to love God above all things quantum ad intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> but only <hi>quantum ad appretiationem;</hi> appretiatively (by way of valuation) that is, if we think God more worthy and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent than all created Beings. How <hi>eaſie</hi> have theſe infallible Doctors made this moſt difficult precept? And yet this is not all; for propounding this Queſtion, <note place="margin">* <hi>Filliuc: Tom:</hi> 2. <hi>trat:</hi> 22. <hi>c:</hi> 9. <hi>p:</hi> 49.</note> when are we engaged to love God? They anſwer <hi>Not above three or four moments in our lives</hi> viz: <hi>when we begin to have the uſe</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">† <hi>Eſcob: Theo Mor: Tract:</hi> 5. <hi>p:</hi> 600.</note> 
                     <hi>of reaſon, at the point of death, and from</hi> 5 <hi>yeares to</hi> 5 <hi>yeares during life.</hi> Others I confeſſe are more liberal and adde five moments more <hi>viz:</hi> When Baptiſm is received by an adult perſon, when con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition is neceſſary, when we receive ſome
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:64645:33"/> are to ſuffer Martyrdome, when the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God is to be defended, and when we are obliged to love our Neighbour; but theſe are rejected by <hi>Filliucius</hi> as ſuperfluous.</p>
                  <p>2. <hi>God commands us to worſhip him in ſpir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t and in truth.</hi> 4 Joh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 24. with all the powers and faculties of the ſoul. But if this ſeem too painful and laborious their Caſuiſts will give you caſe, and tell you that the <hi>Opus operatum</hi> is ſufficient. They teach that it is not neceſſary to the eſſence of prayer, that he who praye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhould think <hi>de ipſa locutione,</hi> of the ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelfe. When its ſaid, we muſt ſay our prayers attently, reverently. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly. <hi>We muſt know</hi> (ſaith Cardinal <note place="margin">* <hi>Inſtruct: Sacerd: lib:</hi> 2. <hi>cap:</hi> 13. <hi>p:</hi> 422.</note> 
                     <hi>Tolet) that attention or Advertency to our prayers is manifold.</hi> 1. <hi>That we attend to to the words, ſo as not to ſpeak them too faſt, or to begin the next verſe, before be that recites with us hath done the former: and this attention is neceſſary.</hi> 2. There <hi>is an attention which is by underſtanding the ſenſe of the words: and that is not neceſſary: For if it were very few would do their duty, becauſe very few underſtand what they ſay.</hi> 3. There <hi>is an attention relating to the end</hi>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:64645:33"/> 
                     <hi>of prayer; when he that praye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> conſiders that he i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in the preſenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of God, and ſpeak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to him; and this is profitable but not neceſſary.</hi> And in the next page he affirms, <hi>that the precept of hearing Maſſe is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to attend the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rds, but to be preſent at the Sacrifice though the words be not ſo much as heard; and they who think otherw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe, think ſo without any probable reaſon.</hi> And <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Tract:</hi> 1. <hi>p:</hi> 174.</note> 
                     <hi>Eſcobar</hi> aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <note place="margin">† <hi>Theol. Mor tract: Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am:</hi> 11. <hi>cap:</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 183.</note> 
                     <hi>that if the external deportment of the body be devout its ſufficient.</hi> Nay this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and poſture of the body is ſufficient (ſaith <hi>Eſcobar</hi> and <hi>Filliucius) though the mind be entertained with thoughts of luſt.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">† <hi>Theol: Mor tom:</hi> 1 <hi>tract:</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 70.</note> 
                     <hi>and vanity.</hi> Thus a man may ſerve God and Satan at the ſame time.</p>
                  <p>3. <hi>God commands us to give almes of ſuch things as we have.</hi> 11 <hi>Luk:</hi> 41. A ſevere Command (faith the covetous Worldling) muſt I give away my Eſtate, that hath coſt me ſo dear, unto I know not whom? I cannot embrace a Religion thats ſo chargeable. O come over to us (ſaith the Romaniſt) and our infallible Guides of conſcience will eaſe you of your pain and trouble. <hi>Eſcobar</hi> handling this Queſtion, <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Theol: Mor tom:</hi> 5. <hi>cap:</hi> 4. <hi>p:</hi> 608.</note> When this precept of giving almes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeth? Anſwers, <hi>that in extream neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:64645:34"/> 
                     <hi>we are obliged to give alms of ſuch things as are not neceſſary unto life, though they be needful to ſupport us in our condition; becauſe the life of our Neighbour</hi> (for by extream neceſſity he underſtands that on which the life of man dependeth) <hi>ought to be preferr'd to the decency of our condition.</hi> And afterwards propounding this Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Whether he that hath more then he needs to live according to his Condition, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>pag:</hi> 609.</note> be obliged to ſupply the common neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of others? He anſwers negatively: and obſerve his doughty reaſon; <hi>becauſe otherwiſe very few rich men would be ſaved.</hi> That is, though a man hath a very plentiful eſtate, more than ſufficient to ſupply his own neceſſities, and thoſe of his Family, yet he is not obliged in a publick Famine to give unto the poor, except it be to ſave his life. And <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>De ſept: peccat: Mort: cap:</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>5. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>:</hi> 1001.</note> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Tolet</hi> tells us that this is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Opinion. Yea diverſe, Caſuiſts have found out a way to exempt even the richeſt perſons from this obligation of giving almes, by interpreting the word <hi>ſuperfluous.</hi> And this is done by the learned <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſquez</hi> in this manner: <hi>What ever men lay up, out of a deſign to raiſe their</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">† <hi>De Eleem: cap:</hi> 4.</note> 
                     <hi>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n fortunes, or thoſe of their Relations, is</hi>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:64645:34"/> 
                     <hi>not called ſuperfluous. For which reaſon it will be hard to find among thoſe that are worldly minded, that have ought ſuperfluous, no not even among Kings.</hi> Thus you ſee that, according to the Rules of theſe Caſuiſts, rich men are rarely, if ever ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to works of Charity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj:</hi> But who are more frequent in works of charity than Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ:</hi> What men give for the redemption of their ſouls from the pains of Purgatory, or the prevention of them, cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be called a work of Charity. He that gives 50 or 100<hi>l.</hi> to the poor to avoid the diſgrace of publick Penance, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piate ſome notorious Crime, cannot hence be denominated a charitable man.</p>
                  <p>4. God commands Women to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt in their habit and attire 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 3: 3: and they muſt not conform to the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt cuſtomes and faſhions of the world. 12 <hi>Rom:</hi> 2. If this diſpleaſe our Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, <hi>Leſſius</hi> will tell them, <hi>that theſe</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">* <hi>De Iuſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> jure lib:</hi> 4. <hi>cap: d:</hi> 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 114 <hi>p:</hi> 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>and ſuch like Scriptures were precepts direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed onely to the women of that time, that by their modeſty they might give ſuch examples</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:64645:35"/> 
                     <hi>as ſhould be for the edification of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And their famous <hi>Eſcobar</hi> (whoſe <note place="margin">* <hi>Theol: Mor tract:</hi> 1. <hi>Exam:</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 135.</note> judgement we muſt not queſtion) poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ms <hi>that when a woman adorns her ſelfe without any wicked deſign (that is, to tempt others to lewdneſſe) by a natural in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination which ſhe hath unto pride, it is but a venial ſin, and ſometimes no ſin at all.</hi> Nay <hi>Layman</hi> ſaith, that <hi>for men to wear Womens, and Women Mens apparel is no ſin.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">† <hi>Theol: Mor lib:</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 242</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>5. God commands us to ſpeak the truth 4 <hi>Eph:</hi> 25. and not to ſwear falſly. 4 <hi>Jer:</hi> 2. But alas (may ſome ſay) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out lying and falſe ſwearing we cannot manage our Trades, ſecure our Concerns, and accompliſh our deſigns. The ſtrict obſervation of theſe precepts would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe us to a thouſand inconveniences. For the eaſe of ſuch mens Conſciences their excellent Caſuiſts have invented three wayes <hi>viz: Equivocation, mental reſervation,</hi> and <hi>directing the intention:</hi> by the help of theſe you may ſay and ſwear what you pleaſe. <hi>In ſwearing it is</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">* <hi>Theol: Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trast:</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Exam:</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 69.</note> 
                     <hi>lawful</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eſcobar) to uſe ambiguous terms, which the hearer may take in another ſenſe than he doth from whom they proceed.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">† <hi>Cap:</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 73.</note>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:64645:35"/> And propounding this Queſtion, <hi>Is it lawful for him that ſweareth in a juſt cauſe to uſe equivocal words, which he underſtands in a ſenſe (which he concealeth) different from that in which thoſe perſons take it before whom the oath is made?</hi> He anſwers affirmatively with <hi>Sanchez.</hi> And to make this more clear, he ſubjoyns ſeveral Inſtances, which are taken out of their moſt famous <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> Leſſius, Sanchez &amp;c. <hi>A man being interrogated by a Judge upon oath, whether he killed S. T. If he killed him in his own defence, he may deny it; waking this mental reſervation, that he did not wickedly murther him. If it be a probable Opinion, that ſuch an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition upon goods is unjuſt, which enforceth the Merchant to uſefalſe weights and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: if he be asked afterwards by a Judge, whether he uſed falſe weights and meaſures, he ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> deny it upon oath; making this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation in his mind, that he did nothing unjuſtly. A Prieſt being interrogated con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch a ſin, which he heard in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, may anſwer, yea and (if need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire) ſwear, that no ſuch thing was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to him, meaning as a private man. Some neceſſary Goods thou hideſt, left they ſhould be ſwept away by thy Creditors, and</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:64645:36"/> 
                     <hi>thou compelled to begge, being asked before a Judge, thou mayeſt ſwear that none are concealed by thee: making this mental re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; which thou art obliged to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover. An Adultereſſe being demaunded of her Husband, whether ſhe hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted adultery; may ſwear negatively: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving in her mind another day than that on which ſhe did commit it. One coming from a place falſly ſuppoſ'd to be infected with the plague, being asked, whether he came thence, may ſwear that he did not; making this mental reſervation, as from a peſtilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial place. If a man borrow a ſumme of money of another, and return it, but taketh no receipt under his hand, and be brought to his oath before a Judge whether he borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any money of him, he may lawfully ſwear, that he never receiv'd any money of him; underſtanding within himſelf, not ſo as to owe it, or that he is obliged to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it.</hi> ſaith <hi>Filliucius.</hi> And in the ſame <note place="margin">† <hi>Quaeſt: Mor:</hi>
                     </note> Queſtion he layes down this general rule: <hi>He that hath externally promiſed ſomething</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">* <hi>Tom:</hi> 2. <hi>tr:</hi> 25. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 107.</note> 
                     <hi>without an intention of promiſing, if he be aſked, whether he promiſed, may upon oath deny it; making this mental reſervation not with a promiſe that obligeth him.</hi> And Queſt: 4. he propounds another way to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:64645:36"/> avoid lying and perjury, much more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure than the former. And that is, when a man having ſaid aloud, <hi>I ſwear that I have not do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e ſuch a thing, he adds, whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering to himſelfe, this day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if any be too thick skull'd to learn this art of making theſe mental reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they have invented a more eaſie way <hi>viz:</hi> ordering and directing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention aright. <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Theol: Mor tract:</hi> 3. <hi>Exam:</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 369.</note> 
                     <hi>Eſcobar</hi> layes down this general rule: <hi>Promiſes oblige not when a man hath no intention to engage himſelfe when he makes them.</hi> If a man falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of Thieves cannot be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed without an oath that he will give them ten Crowne, he is not obliged, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he did intend it at the time of ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Inſtruct: Sacerd: lib:</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 22 <hi>p:</hi> 191.</note> 
                     <hi>Tolet.</hi> And <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Aphor: p.</hi> 98. <hi>Tom:</hi> 2. <hi>tract: cap:</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 107.</note> 
                     <hi>Emanuel Sa</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively affirms: <hi>that he who ſweareth to do this o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> that, is not obliged, if he did not intend by that oath to oblige himſelfe.</hi> And <hi>Filliutius</hi> gives this reaſon for it <hi>becauſe it is the the intention that regulates the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the action.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe Methods their Caſuiſts unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly propound, by which all lyes and perjuries may be juſtifyed. How de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive they are of all commerce, and humane Society is moſt evident.</p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:64645:37"/>
                  <p> 6. God commands us to make reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of ſuch Goods as we have unjuſty taken, or detain'd from others 19. <hi>Luk:</hi> 8. And the Ancients ſay, <hi>that without reſtitution there can be no remiſſion.</hi> But their Caſuiſts have found out many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedients to diſpenſe with this important duty. <hi>Medina, Leſſius,</hi> and <hi>Filliucius</hi> mention twelve cauſes which excuſe from reſtitution; to which many more are added by other Caſuiſts. I will men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <note place="margin">* <hi>Theol: Mor tract:</hi> 3. <hi>Exam:</hi> 2. <hi>cap:</hi> 2. <hi>p:</hi> 337.</note> and but mention, a few of them. 1. <hi>If a man hath done thee wrong without any ill intention, he is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> wiſe obliged to make reſtitution,</hi> ſaith Eſcobar. 2. <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of what kind ſoeven, either of the fact<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>or</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">† <hi>Tract</hi> 3. <hi>Exam:</hi> 2. <hi>c:</hi> 4. <hi>p:</hi> 24.</note> 
                     <hi>of the Law is a ſuffic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ent excuſe.</hi> ſaith the ſame Caſuiſt. And though after ſame enquiry he find it more probable, that the <hi>goods</hi> whereof he is poſſeſſed belong to another, yet he may lawfully keep them, ſaith <hi>Palaus</hi> Cited by <hi>Eſcobar.</hi> And he gives this reaſon; <hi>becauſe poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 350.</note> 
                     <hi>praeponderates all contrary reaſons which are not demonſtrative.</hi> Nay though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he be fully convinced: that they are another mans Goods, yet, if <hi>they be moveable af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter three years enjoyment, and if i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>able,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:64645:37"/> 
                        <hi>after ten years poſſeſſion, he is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> obliged to make reſtitution, ſaith</hi> Filliucius. 3. When another mans Goods are mingled <note place="margin">* <hi>Tom:</hi> 2: <hi>tract:</hi> 32. <hi>c:</hi> 5. <hi>p:</hi> 242.</note> with his own: ſo Leſſius. <hi>A Merchant</hi> (ſaith Eſcobar) <hi>who hath received another mans money, and mingled it with his own,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">∥ <hi>De Juſt: lib:</hi> 2. <hi>p:</hi> 172 <hi>Theol: Mor: tract:</hi> 3. <hi>Exam:</hi> 2. <hi>p:</hi> 350.</note> 
                        <hi>if he to whom the money appertain'd, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund it back again, he is not obliged to reſtore it according to</hi> Vaſquez. 4. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility of doing it without leſſening a mans retinue, and loſſe of honour and <note place="margin">† <hi>Tract:</hi> 3. <hi>Exam:</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> 341. <hi>&amp;</hi> 356</note> reputation: ſo <hi>Eſcobar,</hi> and <hi>Sa</hi> who cites <hi>So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>, Arag:</hi> and <hi>Tolet.</hi> And <hi>Layman</hi> lib: <note place="margin">* <hi>Aphor: p.</hi> 143.</note> 3. t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ract<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. p. 305. <hi>Navar: Manual:</hi> Confeſſ: cap: 17. p. 320. who gives ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral reaſons for it. <hi>Filliucius</hi> Tom: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. tract: 32. cap. 5. p. 243. 5. <hi>When it is a greater diſadvantage to the perſon, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores, than an advantage to the perſon wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">† <hi>Pag:</hi> 356.</note> 
                        <hi>ſaith</hi> Eſcobar (who cites <hi>Tolet)</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> and <hi>Layman.</hi> 6. <hi>When his Confeſſor doth not enjoyn it. Eſcobar.</hi> tract: 3. Exam: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 339. 7. When a man renounceth his <note place="margin">† <hi>Tract:</hi> 3. <hi>Exam:</hi> 2. <hi>p,</hi> 359.</note> Eſtate. <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Apher: p.</hi> 143. <hi>lib:</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 305.</note> 
                     <hi>Eſcobar</hi> putting this Queſtion, whether a man that renounceth his Eſtate, may with a good conſcience retain ſo much as is neceſſary for himſelfe and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily to live in honour, or according to his quality? Anſwers with <hi>Leſſius that</hi>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:64645:38"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:64645:38"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:64645:39"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:64645:39"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:64645:40"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:64645:40"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:64645:41"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:64645:41"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:64645:42"/> 
                     <hi>he may doe it.</hi> Now if we admit theſe excuſes as juſt and lawful (which none muſt queſtion) its moſt clear that few, if any, will be lyable to make reſtitution of thoſe goods which they are moſt unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſeſſed of.</p>
                  <p>7. God commands us to be ſober 2 <hi>Tit:</hi> 12. and to avoid intemperance in eating and drinking 21 <hi>Luk:</hi> 34. But their great <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Tract:</hi> 2. <hi>Exam:</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>cap:</hi> 8. <hi>p:</hi> 294.</note> 
                     <hi>Eſcobar,</hi> who ſpeaks according to the ſentiments of four and twenty of their moſt eminent Caſuiſts, is more indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent: for propounding this Queſtion, <hi>Whether it be lawfull to eat and drink ones fill without neceſſity for pleaſure onely?</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers poſitively with <hi>Sanctius, that it is no ſin at all, except the health of the body be impair'd by that exceſſe.</hi> And he gives this invincible reaſon; <hi>becauſe the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral appetite may be permitted to move ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to its own inclinations, and enjoy the pleaſure it finds therein.</hi> And diſcourſing of intemperance in drinking, he ſtarts this Queſtion: <hi>One drinks to exceſſe, not ſo far as to be drunk, but in ſuch manner that his head akes, or the wine diſturbs him in ſuch ſort, that he knows not very well what he doth; but yet he hath reaſon enough</hi>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:64645:42"/> 
                     <hi>to know that he hath drunk too much.</hi> 
                     <note n="†" place="margin">Layman, Filliucias &amp;c, give this defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of drun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenneſſe: It is an exceſs in drinking for pleaſure onely till the vſe of reaſon be vtterly loſt.</note> 
                     <hi>What kind of ſin is this?</hi> He anſwers, <hi>it is a venial ſin.</hi> And obſerve his reaſon; <hi>becauſe he hath not wholly loſt the uſe of reaſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But perhaps ſome may ſay, though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance in drinking be in it ſelfe but a venial ſin, or none at all; yet the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of that exceſſe <hi>viz:</hi> ſwearing, whoring &amp;c. doubtleſſe a man muſt be accountable for. This ſcruple is remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by their omnipotent Doctors. <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Tract:</hi> 2. <hi>Exam:</hi> 2. <hi>cap:</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 290.</note> 
                     <hi>Eſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar</hi> ſaith, <hi>that a man is not reſponſible for the exceſſes and diſorders which he commits at ſuch a time, if he did not foreſee them before he began to drink.</hi> Cardinal <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Inſtruct: Sacer: lib:</hi> 5. <hi>cap:</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 647.</note> 
                     <hi>Tolet</hi> affirms, <hi>that if a man be drunk, and then commit fornication or murther, that forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or murther is no ſin.</hi> And <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Theol: Mor lib:</hi> 1. <hi>p:</hi> 18.</note> 
                     <hi>Layman</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Murther committed by a man when drunk is no ſin abſtractly conſidered: and he gives this reaſon, becauſe it is no way voluntary and moral in it ſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ariſtotle ſaith, <hi>that drunkards deſerve double puniſhment.</hi> 1. <hi>For their drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">† <hi>Eth: lib: cap.</hi> 5.</note> 2. <hi>For the ſins committed in and by their drunkenneſs.</hi> But what ever <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> or <hi>Plato,</hi> or <hi>Seneca,</hi> or any other Heathen (who had onely the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:64645:43"/> to direct them) ſhall affirm to the contrary; yet we muſt not entertain a disbelieving thought of the truth of theſe poſitions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which are the efforts of an infallible Spirit.</p>
                  <p>8. God Commands us not to take his name in vain 20 <hi>Exod:</hi> 7. But may ſome ſay, we have got a habit of uſing Gods name irreverently upon all occaſions, and when tranſported with paſſion, to utter blaſphemous expreſſions. Be not troubled, your infallible Guides ſpeake very comfortably to your particular caſes, <hi>Lar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> treating of voluntary actions, after he had premiſed certain Concluſions, makes this Inference: <hi>It followes from what I have ſaid, that be who from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of an inveterate cuſtome is induced to doe evil, &amp; to utter words of blaſphemy</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> not at all, nor doth properly blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme; becauſe ſin cannot be committed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a deliberate act of the underſtanding.</hi> And he confirms this Aſſertion by the teſtimony of their great School-men and Caſuiſts, <hi>Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us, Suarez, Sanchez</hi> &amp;c. And the like they ſay of blaſphemies ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd in paſſion; and <hi>Filliucius</hi> gives this reaſon, <hi>becauſe paſſion as well as an evil ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit takes away the actual uſe of reaſon, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:64645:43"/> 
                     <hi>which ſin cannot be committed, according to their</hi> Maximes:</p>
                  <p>9. God Commands us not to render evill for evill. 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 5: 15. But their Caſuiſts teach that a man may repay even the ſmalleſt injury with the greateſt loſſe, that is, of life it ſelfe. In ſeveral caſes (they ſay) it is lawful to murther our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: I will mention but two, which very frequently occur. 1. In defence of our honour. The honour of a perſon <note place="margin">* <hi>Tom:</hi> 2. <hi>tr:</hi> 29. <hi>c:</hi> 3. <hi>p:</hi> 188.</note> may be invaded (ſaith <hi>Filliucius)</hi> ſeveral waies. 1. When one ſtrikes him with a Cudgel, or gives him a box on the ear. <note place="margin">† <hi>And Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> 4. <hi>or</hi> 5. <hi>Wates.</hi>
                     </note> 2. When he is reproached by words or geſtures. 3. When he is accuſed of feigned Crimes before perſons in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or of true, if they be ſecret, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may ſuffer in his perſon or eſtate. <hi>When the honour of a perſon is impair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d by another any of theſe wayes, its lawful to</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">* <hi>De Iuſt: lib:</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 89. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>kill him,</hi> ſaith <hi>Filliutius.</hi> And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme this opinion <hi>Leſſius</hi> produceth <hi>Sot: Navar. Sylveſter, Lopez, Gomez,</hi> and <hi>Julius Clarius,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eſcobar</hi> (who is ſpokesman for twenty <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tract:</hi> 1. <hi>Exam:</hi> 7: <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 120.</note> four learned and antient Divines) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding this Queſtion, <hi>Whether it be</hi>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:64645:44"/> 
                     <hi>lawfull for an honourable perſon to kill him, who hath given him evil language, or the lye?</hi> Anſwers that according to Badel <hi>it is lawful, in caſe he cannot otherwiſe be repreſſed. If a Noble man be aſſaulted, and may ſave himſelfe by flight, yet he is not obliged, but may kill the aſſailant, if otherwiſe his honour cannot be preſerved,</hi> ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Inſtruct: Sacerd: lib:</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>p:</hi> 633.</note> Cardinal Tolet. <hi>It is lawful accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Barnes</hi> (ſaith <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Tract:</hi> 1. <hi>Exam:</hi> 7. <hi>p:</hi> 118.</note> Eſcobar) <hi>to kill that man who intends to accuſe me of ſome capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal crime, which is ſecret, whereupon I may ſuffer death, or a conſiderable loſſe in mine Eſtate, if I can by no means divert him.</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Cited by Auth: of Jeſ: Mor:</note> Amicus and Caramuel affirme <hi>that a Monk may kill a Woman with whom he hath committed fornication, if he fear ſhe will divulge it.</hi> Theſe Inſtances doe plainly evidence the lawfulneſſe of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (according to the ſentiments of their infallible Doctors) in defence of a mans honour and reputation. But here this one rule muſt be obſerved <hi>viz: That we doe not kill with a formal intention to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">† <hi>Leſſius de Juſt: lib:</hi> 2. <hi>p:</hi> 89.</note> 
                     <hi>our ſelves, but to preſerve our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. In defence of our Goods. So much is affirmed by <hi>Layman,</hi> and he cites <hi>Anton:</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>lib:</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 354</note> 
                     <hi>Major, Sylveſier, Cajetan, Soto, Navar:</hi>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:64645:44"/> 
                     <hi>Covarr: Clarus, Medina, Moliua</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Leſſius</hi> gives this reaſon for it; <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe temporal goods are neceſſary to preſerve</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">* <hi>Lib:</hi> 2. <hi>p:</hi> 85. <hi>&amp;</hi> 88.</note> 
                     <hi>life, and by conſequence it is lawful to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them in the ſame manner as life it ſelfe.</hi> Nay he affirmes <hi>that its lawful to</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ibid:</note> 
                     <hi>kill a perſon, that hath taken an Apple from us, if it would be a diſgrace unto us not to take it out of the Thieves hands.</hi> But <hi>Molina</hi> (and <hi>Eſcobar</hi> ſeems to concurre <note place="margin">† <hi>Tract:</hi> 1. <hi>Exam</hi> 7. <hi>p:</hi> 119.</note> with him) thinks that <hi>ordinarily it is not lawful to kill for leſſe than a Crown or the value of it.</hi> And if theſe Inſtances be not ſufficient, <hi>Eſcobar</hi> layes down this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <note place="margin">* <hi>Tract:</hi> 1. <hi>Exam:</hi> 7. <hi>p:</hi> 112.</note> Rule, that will juſtify moſt Murthers in the world: <hi>We may kill thoſe that doe us wrong, as thoſe that rob by night or by day, and all others that offend us, though we be aſſured that they ſhall be damn'd, dying in that condition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>10. God ſaith thou ſhalt not ſteal. 20 <hi>Exod:</hi> 15. But their Caſuiſts teach that in ſeveral caſes theſt is lawful, or at the moſt but a venial ſin; whereby poor men, Children, Servants &amp;c. are encouraged to commit rapes and robberies. To make this clear and evident I will produce a few Inſtances out of theſe miraculous
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:64645:45"/> Doctors. If a man be in neceſſity, not only extream, but ſuch as is ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to be endur'd, <hi>its lawful for him to ſteal for his more comfortable ſubſiſtance.</hi> Leſſius lib: 2. cap. 12. num: 71. p. 132. Filliu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius Tom: 2. tract: 32. cap. 5. p. 243.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If a Father deny his Child employ'd in his Call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ng, as much for his Salary, as he would give unto a Stranger, he may privately take what is proportionable to his labour and in luſtry; when he hath deducted what his Father laid out in his Education.</hi> Eſcobar tract: 1. Exam: 9. cap. 4. p. 158.</p>
                  <p>If Servants judge their wages too ſmall, they may advance them of themſelves by filching and purloyning as much from their Maſters, as they imagine neceſſary to make their wages anſwerable to their ſervices. <hi>Layman</hi> lib: 3. tract: 3. p. 313. and he confirms this Opinion by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of <hi>Navar: Lopez, Licent: Diez, Leſſius, Molina.</hi> I remember the Author of the Myſtery of Jeſuitiſme tells us a pleaſant Story of one <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n D' Albae</hi> in the year 1647, who being a Servant to the Fathers of the Colledge of <hi>Clermont,</hi> and thinking his wages too low, ſtole ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to make it up. Hereupon they put
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:64645:45"/> him in priſon, and charged him with Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony. This poor fellow being arraign'd, confeſt that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e had taken away certain pewter Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es from them: but pleaded that he was not guilty of felony for ſo doing: and urged for his juſtification this Poſition of their Caſuiſts, which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Judges. And if they judge their Diet too courſe and ſcanty, theſe comfortable Caſuiſts will tell them, <hi>that</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">† <hi>Leſſius lib:</hi> 2. <hi>p:</hi> 130.</note> 
                     <hi>what thefts they commit in meats and drinks are not mortal ſins, though inſenſibly they</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">* <hi>Eſcobar: tr:</hi> 1. <hi>Exam:</hi> 9. <hi>p.</hi> 157.</note> 
                     <hi>amount to a great quantity, if they ſteal them to eat and drink, and not to ſell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If that which is ſtoln be ſomething the Owner makes ſmall account of, or for which he would not have the Robber put into a ſtate of damnation</hi> (and who can be ſo cruel as to deſire the eternal miſery of his fellow Creature) <hi>the theft is at the moſt but a venial ſin.</hi> Leſſius lib. 2. cap. 41. dub. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. num: 80. p. 537. <hi>And if a Tayler, who is commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion'd by a Gentleman to buy ſtuffe or ſilk to make his Cloaths, go commonly to one Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer or Merchant, who for this reaſon ſell: him a good pennyworth, or returns ſomthing back: he may retain to himſelf the benefit of his good market, or what is ſo return'd.</hi> Eſcobar tract. 3. Exam: 6. cap, 5. p. 406.</p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:64645:46"/>
                  <p> To theſe Inſtances many more might be added, which do countenance and juſtify moſt thefts and robberies commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this licentious age.</p>
                  <p>By this Induction of particulars (for its needleſſe to mention more) you may ſee how farre they diſpenſe with Divine Commands. They that would ſee more upon this Subject, let them peruſe the Jeſuits Morals, of which I have made very little uſe, no not ſo much as an <hi>hand</hi> to direct me to the places and paſſages which I have produced.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. II.</head>
                  <p>Obj:</p>
                  <p>THeſe are the Opinions of ſome particular Caſuiſts, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps have been conſured by his Holyneſſe as Erroneous, and Heretical.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ:</hi> 1. I doe not hear that any of theſe Doctors (except <hi>Baunies</hi> Summarie of ſins, which I have made no uſe of) are cenſured at Rome, nor find any paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in them, which their <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> command to be blotted out in any of their <hi>Expurgatory Indices.</hi> And therefore (ſince they are ſo ſevere in prohibiting
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:64645:46"/> Books which they judge erroneous, and expunging all offenſive paſſages) we may rationally conclude that theſe <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> have written nothing contrary to the ſentiments of their infallible <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter.</hi> If they deliver any thing which is not conſonant to their <hi>Canons</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions,</hi> why are they not put into their <hi>Index</hi> of prohibited Books?</p>
                  <p>2. The Doctors I have mention'd are no pitiful, obſcure Fellows, but perſons of great note and eminency, and their Books printed <hi>cum Privilegio,</hi> and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prized by all Catholicks.</p>
                  <p>3. That where I have Cited but one or two <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> ten or twenty might be produced, which I have paſſed over for brevity ſake.</p>
                  <p>4. The Doctrine of <hi>probability</hi> (which is unanimouſly received by their great Doctors, at leaſt the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> which are the moſt prevailing partie in the Church of Rome, and the Popes principal <hi>Factors)</hi> will remove all doubts and ſcruples. Here they lay down with much confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and defend with great zeal theſe following propoſitions.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That we may ſafely follow a <hi>proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Opinion.</hi> In this there is a perfect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:64645:47"/> amongſt them: and <hi>Layman</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">† <hi>Lib</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>: <hi>p:</hi> 5.</note> gives this reaſon for it; <hi>becauſe in Morals we cannot eaſily obtain a certain knowledge of the truth of things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. That is a probable Opinion, which (having no certainty) is ſupported by great <hi>Authority,</hi> or ſome reaſon of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p:</hi> 5.</note> So <hi>Layman</hi> defines a probable Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. And in the explication of this definition he tells us that by <hi>(great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority)</hi> we are to underſtand the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at leaſt of one learned and honeſt man, that hath not embraced an Opinion raſhly and inconſiderately, but after he hath well weigh'd and examin'd the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which are brought for the contrary Opinion. <hi>Eſcobar</hi> ſaith <hi>that one grave</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Theol: Mor: p.</hi> 25.</note> 
                     <hi>Doctor is able to make an Opinion probable; becauſe a man eminently learned will not eſpouſe an Opinion without ſufficient reaſon. Emanuel Sa</hi> ſpeaks more freely, affirming <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aphor: p. p.</hi> 41.</note> 
                     <hi>that the judgement of one grave Doctor, or the example of good men is enough to make an Opinion probable.</hi> And to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſpeak <hi>Sylveſt: Navar. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſquez,</hi> and <hi>Sanchez</hi> cited by <hi>Layman. Filliucius</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares himſelfe to be of the ſame judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Tom: 2. tr: 21. cap. 4. p. 9.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:64645:47"/> 3 That of two probable <hi>Opinions</hi> its lawful to follow that which is more favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able though leſſe ſafe and probable. This <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Theol: Mor: Lib:</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 5.</note> propoſition is defended by <hi>Layman,</hi> who brings <hi>Navar. Medina, Arrag: Lopez, Suarez, Azorius</hi> &amp;c. concurring with him. And if the teſtimony of theſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Doctors be not ſufficient, he gives you this convincing reaſon: <hi>In moral actions it is not neceſſary to follow that which is beſt and ſafeſt; but ſufficient that we follow what is good and ſafe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>Eſcobar</hi> propounding this Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>If two probable Opinions occur, is a</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 27.</note> 
                     <hi>man obliged to follow that which is more probable?</hi> He anſwers <hi>no; becauſe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be reprehended as raſh and imprudent, who adhaeres to reaſon or authority of moment: and it would be an intollerable burthen, if every unlearned man ſhould be obliged to</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Inſtit: Mor: lib:</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 202</note> 
                     <hi>find out the more probable Opinions.</hi> But <hi>Azorius</hi> aſcends one ſtep higher, and ſaith <hi>that a man may lawfully follow the probable Opinion of other men, though it be againſt his own proper Opinion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus a man may commit any ſin (to which intereſt, or corrupt nature ſhall incline him) againſt his own Conſcience, if he can but find out one grave Doctor
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:64645:48"/> that allowes it: and thats no difficult taſke.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That a <hi>Confeſſor</hi> is oblig'd to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve his <hi>Penitent,</hi> who followes a proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Opinion,</hi> though contrary to his own <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib:</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 205.</note> judgement. <hi>Azorius</hi> handling this Queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Whether a Prieſt who hears Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, may reaſonably ſubmit to the Opinion of his Penitent, when 'tis contrary to his own?</hi> After he hath propounded the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions and limitations of ſeveral <hi>Doctors,</hi> affirms <hi>that in every caſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception or diſtinction, every Confeſſor, as well ordinary as delegate, may and ought to ſubmit to the judgement of his Penitent. As for example, ſuppoſe the Confeſſor is fully convinced that his Penitent is obliged to make reſtitution of goods unjuſtly detain'd, and hereupon ſcruples to abſolve him; yet if the Penitent will not ſubmit unto his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he may doe it.</hi> And obſerve his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; <hi>becauſe he who hears the confeſſions of Penitents is oblig'd to provide for their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Layman</hi> affirms the ſame thing, and <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib:</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 6.</note> tells us that <hi>Sot: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictor: Navar. Medina, Sanchez,</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſquez</hi> are of this perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And he gives this weighty reaſon for it: <hi>The Confeſſor, confeſſion being made,</hi>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:64645:48"/> 
                     <hi>cannot deny abſolution to his Penitent that is rightly diſpoſ'd: but in following a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Opinion, the Penitent doth not ſin, and ſo, as to this, is rightly diſpoſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>Eſcobar</hi> propounding the ſame Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, returns the ſame anſwer, and gives the ſame reaſon. Nay he addes, <hi>that the Confeſſor, who denies abſolution upon this account, is guilty of mortal ſin, when the ſins confeſſed are mortal; becauſe he forceth his Penitent to diſcover thoſe ſins to another Confeſſor, which is a grievous burthen.</hi> Theol: Mor: p. 28. To theſe I could adde the teſtimony of <hi>Filliucius,</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Tom: p:</hi> 113.</note> Cardinal <hi>Tolet,</hi> and many others.</p>
                  <p>Now what wickedneſſe may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib:</hi> 3. 51<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> under the protection of this Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is obvious to an ordinary under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. How doth it favour looſe and licentious perſons, and indulge them in their immoralities; for what Crime can be committed, but ſome one or other of their Doctors doth allow and juſtifie it?</p>
                  <p>Canſt thou not keep what thou art poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of, nor recover what is unjuſtly detain'd from thee without the aſſiſtance of a <hi>Knight</hi> of the <hi>Poſt,</hi> that is, without ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>borning a perſon to ſwear falſly? doe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:64645:49"/> not boggle at it; for <hi>Filliucius</hi> (a grave and learned <hi>Doctor,</hi> yea the Popes Peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiarie) <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tom:</hi> 2. <hi>p:</hi> 108.</note> teacheth that in this caſe its very lawful. Onely he ſubjoynes this caution: <hi>That ſomething of value be in queſtion, and that there be ſome juſt cauſe to require this oath, as neceſſity or profit; otherwiſe it would be againſt charity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Haſt thou weaken'd thy body in Brothel-houſes, or by the ſin of uncleaneſſe, and canſt not without great prejudice to thy health obſerve an approaching Lent, or time of faſting according to the <hi>Canons</hi> of the Church? Be not troubled; for in this very caſe (ſaith <hi>Eſcobar</hi> a Doctor of great note and eminencie) thou art ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſ'd. <hi>Theol: Mor: tr:</hi> 1. <hi>Exam:</hi> 13. cap. 2. p. 198. Yea though thou didſt it on purpoſe to be diſpenſed withal from faſting. p. 202.</p>
                  <p>Haſt thou the offer of a good Benefice, but upon condition that thou wilt give ſo much money unto the Incumbent to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, or Patron to preſent; which thou art willing to doe, but a thing they call Simony, is as a Lyon in the way, deters thee from it. Be not troubled, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentia</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">* <hi>Tom:</hi> 3: <hi>p.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>039.</note> (one of their chiefeſt School-men and Caſuiſts) will help thee to conjure down
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:64645:49"/> this tormenting Spirit. <hi>If a man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>give a temporal good for a ſpiritual</hi> (that is, money for a Benefice) <hi>and that a man give money as the price of the Benefice, it is apparent Simony. But if he gives it as the motive inclining the will of the Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent to reſign his intereſt, it is no Sim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Thus do but direct thine intention ſo, as to give thy money as a <hi>motive</hi> inclining the Patron, or Incumbent, and not as the <hi>price</hi> of the Benefice, and thou art ſafe enough.</p>
                  <p>Thus might we inſtance in moſt ſins, and produce one or more of their <hi>indulgent Doctors</hi> that allow them: and ſo (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Probability)</hi> they may be commttied without ſin. Our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> ſaith <hi>that norrow is the way that leadeth unto life, and few there be that find it.</hi> 7 <hi>Math:</hi> 14: but theſe infallible <hi>Doctors</hi> make it broad, and according to their <hi>Poſitions</hi> few can miſſe of it: it is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eaſie to be ſaved, but almoſt impoſible to be damned.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj:</hi> But doe we not meet with ſome great <hi>Schoolmen</hi> and <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> that do not allow of theſe irregularities?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ:</hi> Yes; but they are few, and very rarely made uſe of. It being their <hi>deſign</hi>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:64645:50"/> to bring the whole world into the boſome of the Roman Church by complying with the various humours and inclinations of men, its neceſſary they ſhould have ſuch: And becauſe the <hi>Maximes</hi> of Evangelical ſeverity are more convenient for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of ſome, they make uſe of them upon ſuch occaſions as contribute to the promoting of this deſign. I ſay, being to deal with all ſorts of perſons, and thoſe of ſeveral conditions, and different Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, its requiſite they ſhould have <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſts</hi> ſuitable to this diverſity. If they had not any but theſe licentious <hi>Doctors,</hi> their main deſign (which is to deceive the world) would be fruſtrated; ſince thoſe who have any ſenſe of good and evil, any tenderneſſe of conſcience, and care of their ſouls put themſelves under a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er conduct: But as there are not many of this ſcrupulous humour, ſo need they but few ſevere <hi>Directors</hi> to guide them. Few ſheep need fewer Shepherds; whereas the ſwarm of remiſſe <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> are employ'd to ſatisfie thoſe who ſeek after carnal li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie. It is by this obliging and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying <hi>Conduct</hi> that ſo many are deluded. If one come to them who is reſolved to make reſtitution of goods unjuſtly gotten,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:64645:50"/> they will not divert him, but have a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſt</hi> ready to confirm him in ſo holy a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution: But let another come that would be abſolved without reſtitution, and it ſhall go very hard, but they will contrive a way to diſmiſſe him with ſatisfaction. Thus doe they preſerve their Friends by indulging their particular luſts, and make their party good againſt all Enemies, when charged with remiſneſſe, by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as neceſſity requires) theſe auſtere <hi>Directors</hi> upon the ſtage.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect:</hi> 3.</head>
                  <p>BUt if there be any ſins which cannot be excuſ'd, and whereof the onely remedy is <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> yet theres no reaſon why any one ſhould be troubled; for this by their <hi>Doctrines</hi> they have made moſt eaſie: ſo that crimes are with greater fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility expiated, than many times com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. Whereas there are many things in <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> that cannot be performed without ſome difficulty, <hi>as ſhame to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe ſome certain ſins, reſolution not to fall into the like again, remorſe for them, and Penance;</hi> yet they have made moſt eaſie and comfortable proviſions againſt them. This main part of their Religion, which
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:64645:51"/> hath the appearance of ſeverity, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of all other moſt remiſſe and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and of greateſt content even to the diſſoluteſt minds. This, as they have order'd it, is ſo farre from deterring men from ſin, that it is the moſt powerful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centive to impiety. <q>I have known (ſaith <hi>Sands)</hi> thoſe that ſeem very devout <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Europae: Specul: p.</hi> 11</note> perſons, who by their own report, to excuſe their acquaintance in matters criminal, have wittingly perjured themſelves in judgment; onely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming upon this preſent and eaſy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy of confeſſion: and others of more then ordinary note amongſt them, who when their time of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing was at hand, would then ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on thoſe actions, which before they trembled at; as preſuming to ſurfeit by reaſon of Neighbour hood with the Phyſitian.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againſt the firſt thing in confeſſion <hi>viz:</hi> ſhame, they have made full proviſion. Their <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> teach that a man to preſerve his reputation with his ordinary Confeſſor, may take another, to whom he may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe his groſſe ſins. <hi>Emanuel Sa Aphor:</hi> p. 25. <hi>Eſcobar</hi> tr: 7. Exam: 4. p. 788. <hi>Filliutius</hi> Tom: 1. tr: 7. cap. 4. p. 94.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:64645:51"/> But if this way be too troubleſome and coſtly, <hi>Eſcobar</hi> directs you to make a general Confeſſion. <hi>When one ſaith to his Confeſſor, that he will make a generall confeſſion, he is not obliged to mention his mortal ſins, Eſcob:</hi> p. 785. And what <hi>Filliucius</hi> ſaith of the ſecond and third <hi>viz:</hi> reſolution, and remorſe, is very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tom:</hi> 1. <hi>tr:</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 12. <hi>p.</hi> 112.</note> both to Confeſſors and Penitents. <hi>The Confeſſor</hi> (ſaith be) <hi>muſt not propound many difficulties in avoiding ſin, whence the Penitent may be in danger of not having an effectual purpoſe for the future.</hi> And then afterwards he addeth, <hi>it is not neceſſary that the Confeſſor be aſſur'd, or probably thinke, that his Penitent will abſtain from ſin: its ſufficient if he conceive that at the time of abſolution he hath a general purpoſe, though he will preſently alter it. And this is the common Opinion.</hi> And concerning remorſe he writes, <hi>That if the Penitent diſcover not ſufficient expreſſions of ſorrow, the Confeſſor hath no more to doe than to ask him, whether he doe not in his ſoul de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſin; and if he ſay Yes, he may, nay he muſt believe him.</hi> And <hi>Eſcobar</hi> ſpeaks much to the ſame purpoſe. Tract: 7. Exam: 4. p. 773. It hath been an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion long received in the Schooles, that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:64645:52"/> the Sacraments of the New Law differed from thoſe of the Old in this, that the efficacy of thoſe of the old Law in confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring grace, did depend upon what they called <hi>opus operantis,</hi> that is, the faith and devotion of the receiver of them: but that the Sacraments of the new Law did confer grace <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> that is, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vid: Bellar: De Sacram: Concil: Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: Seſs:</hi> 7. <hi>Can:</hi> 8.</note> by the thing it ſelfe without any depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance therein upon the internal motion or preparation of mind in him that did partake of them. Now this with the Papiſts is a Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>And touching the laſt <hi>viz:</hi> Penance they are not leſſe favourable and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. This conſiſteth ordinarily in a few <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> and <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> and hearing ſo many Maſſes, with ſome eaſie almes to them that are able, and ſome little faſting to them that are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. I have known (ſaith <hi>Sands)</hi> when <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 12.</note> 
                     <q>the Pennance for horrible and often blaſphemy, beſides much other lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, hath been no other than the bare ſaying of their beads thrice over; a matter of ſome hours muttering, and which in <hi>Italy</hi> they diſpatch alſo as they goe in the ſtreets, or diſpatch buſyneſſe at home; making no other
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:64645:52"/> of it, than as it is, two lips and one fingers work.</q> We will make this more clear by the teſtimony of their famous <hi>Caſuiſts.</hi> Sometimes a Prieſt may impoſe this for Penance upon his Confitent <hi>viz: That before he ſleeps at night, and when he awakes in the morning, he entertain ſome pious meditations, that he think of God, and death, and judgment</hi> &amp;c. Layman lib: 5. p. 909. <hi>If the Penitent hath but a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable cauſe to complain of his Penance, as too grievous, the Confeſſor muſt moderate it, or enjoyn ſome other, more eaſy, Layman</hi> ibid: And a little after he gives this caution to the Confeſſor: <hi>Let him take heed that he doe not impoſe incongruous and unſuitable Penances, as long pilgrimages to Women, many prayers to them that have much buſyneſſe</hi> &amp;c. in ſhort, not any thing that is tedious and troubleſome. <hi>A Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor</hi> (ſaith the ſame <hi>Caſuiſt) is oblig'd</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ibid:</note> 
                     <hi>to abſolve his Penitent, though he refuſe to performe the penance enjoyned him.</hi> And he tells us this is the Opinion of Cajetan, <hi>Sylveſter, Medina,</hi> and <hi>Navar.</hi> And gives this reaſon; <hi>becauſe no man is bound to ſatisfy for his ſins in this life.</hi> A <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor</hi> may ſometimes impoſe Penance by way of Counſel onely (ſaith <hi>Filliutius)</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tom:</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 125.</note>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:64645:53"/> and not of precept. Nay be may abſolve without any Penance at all ſaith the ſame <hi>Doctor.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eſcobar</hi> propounds this Queſtion, <hi>Is</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 795.</note> 
                     <hi>it lawful for a Confeſſor to leave it wholly to the will of the Penitent to doe what Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance he pleaſeth? And anſwers with</hi> Suarez, <hi>that it is not alwayes neceſſary to command him any particular work, and eſpecially to ſpiritual perſons: but its ſufficient to ſay, I impoſe on you for Penance all the good you ſhall doe, or evil that you ſhall ſuffer this day, or this week.</hi> And <hi>Filliucius</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms it by the teſtimony of <hi>Aquinas,</hi> and <hi>Navar.</hi> Tom: 1. p. 125. And he commends it as a thing both <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>pleaſant.</hi> And the ſame <hi>Eſcobar</hi> tells us <hi>that a Confeſſor may give for Penance ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing formerly commanded;</hi> ſo that Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance <note place="margin">ibid:</note> for ſins may be accomplſhed by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which we ſhould have done though we had not ſinned, and which the moſt innocent are obliged to. And herein he hath the concurrence of <hi>Sa,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aphor: p.</hi> 147. <hi>Tom:</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 125.</note> and <hi>Filliutius.</hi> And again, aſking the Queſtion, <hi>Whether may my penance be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd by another.</hi> He anſwers <hi>that this is the Opinion of</hi> Suarez (yea and he might ſay of <hi>Sa</hi> and <hi>Filliucius) provided I have</hi>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:64645:53"/> 
                     <hi>my Confeſſors leave, or there be ſome juſt reaſon for it:</hi> And that will never be wanting. Thus eaſy and acceptable have theſe tender and indulgent Fathers, made this moſt difficult part of Confeſſion.</p>
                  <p>I know they make a great cry and cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor; and tell us of their frequent faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, of their often watchings, of their bloody whippings, of their long pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, their rigorous diſcipline, and a great deal more: But what are the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes of ſome few ſad and phlegmatick perſons, to the profeſſed principles of their great Doctors and Caſuiſts?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect:</hi> 4.</head>
                  <p>BUt ſuppoſe the Penance which the Prieſt enjoyns be never ſo ſharp &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere yet let none be diſcourag'd or deterr'd from their beloved luſts; for though it be their misfortune to fall into the hands of a truel Confeſſor, yet they have a merciful Father (to whom they may appeal in ſuch caſes) who by his gracious Indulgences is ready to diſpenſe with theſe ſeverities.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Pardons and Indulgences are very full, and numerous: few Churches in Rome, which have not one or more annexed to them: ſo that if you will but
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:64645:54"/> trudge thither, you cannot miſſe of Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. And ſo kinde they have been at Rome, as to publiſh a <hi>Catalogue</hi> of them in ſeveral Books. And though this was put forth in our own language ſeveral years ago by Mr. <hi>Craſhaw,</hi> yet (becauſe the Book is hard to be got, and perhaps few have ſeen it) a few <hi>Inſtances</hi> take as followeth.</p>
                  <p>In the Church of St. <hi>John the Lateran</hi> there is an inexhauſtable ſtock of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences granted by Pope <hi>Silveſter</hi> at the requeſt of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperour. Whoever comes to this Church on the 9th of <hi>November</hi> may obtain remiſſion of all his ſins both <hi>a poena &amp; culpa.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the ſame Church there is a Chappel called <hi>Sancta Sanctorum,</hi> in which every day is to be had full remiſſion of all ſins. And not farre from this Chappel there is an aſcent of three and thirty ſteps, and how oft ſoever any man ſhall devoutly aſcend up that ladder, for every ſtep he hath a thouſand years of pardon. But who will take ſo much pains when a plenary pardon may be had upon eaſier termes?</p>
                  <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tican there is full remiſſion of all ſins up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Feaſt of St. <hi>Martin:</hi> and at other
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:64645:54"/> times many thouſand years pardon.</p>
                  <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Paul</hi> without the walls of Rome in the Octaves of the Feaſt day of St. <hi>Martin</hi> (being the day on which it was dedicated by Pope <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſter)</hi> there is to be obtain'd full remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all ſins.</p>
                  <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Mary</hi> on the day of Annunciation of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> theres full pardon of all ſins to be had, granted by Pope <hi>Boniface.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the Church of St <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> there is to be got <hi>true remiſſion of all ſins, bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and light everlaſting, joy and gladneſſe without end.</hi> And this Indulgence was merited by that Saint and Martyr to this Church, and confirmed by Pope <hi>Gregorie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Croſſe</hi> there is a Chappel called <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> wherein up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on St. <hi>Benets</hi> day we may obtain full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of all ſins. And upon every <hi>Lords day</hi> and <hi>Wedneſday</hi> there are Pardons for many thouſand years granted by Pope <hi>Silveſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Praxade</hi> theres a Chappel called the Garden of Paradiſe, in which lie the bodies of above two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Martyrs, and the third part of that Pillar at which our Lord Jeſus Chriſt
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:64645:55"/> was whipped in Pilates houſe, there is every day to be had full remiſſion of all ſins.</p>
                  <p>Neither hath the charity of his Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe been confin'd to the Churches of Rome, but enlarged and extended to many other Churches of note in <hi>Italy,</hi> and other Countries.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>In the <hi>Eremitane</hi> at <hi>Padova,</hi> their <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Europae Speculum p.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </note> Preachers very ſolemnly (ſaith <hi>Sands)</hi> publiſh a grant of plenatie Indulgence from Baptiſm to the laſt Confeſſion, with twenty eight yeares over for the time enſuing.</p>
                     <p>At the <hi>Sepulchre</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>Venice,</hi> wherein is written, <hi>Hic ſitum eſt corpus</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>p.</hi> 14.</note> 
                        <hi>Domini noſtri Jeſu Chriſti;</hi> there is hanging in a printed table a Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> with Indulgence for fourſcore and two thouſand yeares, granted by <hi>Boniface</hi> 8. and confirm'd by <hi>Benedict</hi> 11, unto every one that ſhall ſay it, and that for every day <hi>toties quoties.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> 13 hath granted to the <hi>Carmine</hi> at <hi>Padova,</hi> unto every one <note place="margin">
                           <hi>p.</hi> 15.</note> that ſhall ſay 7 <hi>Aves</hi> and 7 <hi>Pater-Noſters</hi> before one of their Altars on the anniverſarie Wedneſday in <hi>Eaſter-week,</hi>
                        <pb n="85" facs="tcp:64645:55"/> or elſe kiſſe the ground before the Altar of the bleſſed Sacrament with the uſual Prayers for exaltation of the Church, extirpation of Hereſy, and Unitie of Chriſtian Princes, both plenary Indulgence for himſelfe, and the delivery of what Friends ſoul out of Purgatory he pleaſes.</p>
                     <p>All Altars of <hi>Station</hi> (which are in very great number) have their perpetual Indulgences for all times.</p>
                     <p>Sundry <hi>Croſſes</hi> engraven on the pave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their Churches have Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence annexed for every time they are kiſt, which is done ſo often by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouter ſex, that the hard Marble is wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> with it.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>By theſe few Inſtances (which are not the fortieth part of what might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced) you may ſee what an indulgent Father his Holyneſſe is; to whom Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents may appeal when their Penances are too ſevere, and what comfortable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion he hath made for them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect:</hi> 5.</head>
                  <p>NEither is their condition hopeleſſe and helpleſſe, who live in <hi>England, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> or any other remote
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:64645:56"/> 
                     <hi>Countries,</hi> and either cannot, or will not trudge to Rome to be made partakers of theſe plenarie Indulgences: His Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath made ample proviſion for theſe alſo, and extended his bounty to them. If it be their miſ-hap to fall into the hands of an ill-natur'd Confeſſor (which very few do) that enjoyns them Penances too tedious and troubleſome, yet they have their relief and remedie <hi>viz:</hi> the Popes pardon at an eaſie rate. And ſo kind hath this holy Father been to his Children, as to put forth a Book called <hi>Taxa S. Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellaria Apoſtolicae</hi> (that they may know before they act any Villany what an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution will coſt) wherein a price is ſet upon moſt ſins; of which take this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Taſte.</p>
                  <p>An Abſolution for a <hi>Biſhop, Abbot,</hi> or the <hi>General</hi> of any <hi>Order</hi> who hath killed a man is rated at about—100 <hi>Groſſos</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If a Lay-man kill an Abbot, a Monk, <note place="margin">* <hi>A Groſſo is ſometimes valued at two pence, ſometimes at</hi> 4 <hi>pence farthing of our Engliſh money.</hi>
                     </note> a Clerk, or other Prieſt leſſe than a Biſhop, he muſt pay for his Abſolution according to the Quality of the perſon—7, 8, or 9. <hi>Gr:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If a Layman kill a Layman he ſhall pay but—6 <hi>Groſ:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If a Woman be with Child and on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe deſtroyeth the Infant within her,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:64645:56"/> ſhall have an Abſolution for—5 <hi>Groſ:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If a man kill his Father, Mother, or Brother, he muſt pay for his Abſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on—1 <hi>Ducat</hi> and 5 <hi>Carlins.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">† <hi>A Carli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> it often the ſame with a Groſſo.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if a man kill his Wife, he muſt not have a farthing abated of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſumme.</p>
                  <p>An Abſolution for him who lyeth with a Woman in the Church is valued at—6 <hi>Groſ:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Every Prieſt that keeps a Concubine muſt pay for his Abſolution—7 <hi>Groſ:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if he be a Lay-man he muſt pay—8 <hi>Groſ:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>An Abſolution for him that deflowers a Vitgin, is dog cheap at—6 <hi>Groſ:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If a Nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne commit fornication either within the Monaſtery or without, ſhe cannot expect an Abſolution under—9 <hi>Duc:</hi> 30 <hi>Gr:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If a man carnally lye with his Mother, Siſter or other Kinſwoman, or God-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he ſhall have his Abſolution at a very eaſy rate—5 <hi>Groſ:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If a Layman commit Sacriledge by tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holy things out of holy places, let him not complain, if he pay for his Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution no more than—7 <hi>Groſ:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Every one that hath broken his Vow of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:64645:57"/> perpetual Chaſtity, muſt pay for his Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution—2 <hi>Duc:</hi> 20 <hi>Groſ</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If a Prieſt commit Simony, he ſhall have his Abſolution upon very eaſy terms, paying—7 <hi>Groſ:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if a perſon be guilty of that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid ſin of perjury, he may obtain an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution for—6 <hi>Groſ:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That there is ſuch a <hi>Book,</hi> is no fiction but a real truth, and moſt clear from the pregnant teſtimonies of their own <hi>Writers,</hi> which no <hi>Romaniſt</hi> can object againſt.</p>
                  <p>This Book was ſet forth by Pope <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>In Titum: p.</hi> 67. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> 10. and thus cenſured by <hi>Claudi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us</hi> a famous <hi>Doctor</hi> of <hi>Sorbon: Let a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> this be held feigned, and falſly charged upon us by the Lutherans, were it not that the Book it ſelfe being come from Rome, is openly ſet to ſale. A Book wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>in thou may<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt learn more wickedneſſe, then w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ever y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> diſcovered in all the Summiſts and Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maries of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, that are extant in all the world. A ſhamefull Book, a very I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> pointing men the way to the moſt foul<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and hateful ſins. So that I am perſwaded there was never ſet out in</hi> Germany, Hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eria,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:64645:57"/> 
                     <hi>nor among any of our enemies that are fallen from us, any Book that bred more ſcandal, or did more hurt to the Roman Church.</hi> But<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> leaſt theſe paſſages ſhould diſcredit their Wares and ſpoil their <hi>Markets,</hi> they have, commanded them to be blotted out in their <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p:</hi> 60.</note> 
                     <hi>Spaniſh Exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rgatory Index.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Doctor <hi>Peter</hi> de <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>liu</hi> ſaith that this <note place="margin">* <hi>De Monar: Temporal: Pon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>: Rom: p.</hi> 355.</note> 
                     <hi>Book</hi> was reprinted at <hi>Paris</hi> by <hi>To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us Dionyſins</hi> in St. <hi>James</hi> his ſtreet at the <hi>Wooden Croſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> the Kings priviledge, and the Popes Bull being annexed to it. And the Lord <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rrey</hi> hath th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe words: <hi>The Books of the Taxes of the Apoſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eal Chaunc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ry, and Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, which yet</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Myſt: Iniq: p.</hi> 656.</note> 
                     <hi>are ſold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nted at this very ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> in</hi> Paris, <hi>at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ign of the</hi> Golden Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> St.</hi> Jaques <hi>Street; and theſe Books are no leſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e commonly uſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orkans, then Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nders with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, or the Book of Cuſtomes and E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ies among <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>:</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">* Lection: Memorab:</note> And <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lfir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> gives us a large account of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Henry<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Fouli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> who had the benefit <note place="margin">* <hi>Tom:</hi> 2: <hi>p.</hi> 825. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> of the publick <hi>Library</hi> in <hi>Oxford)</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> that when that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Collect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> called <hi>Tract at us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> was printed by the King <hi>of France</hi> his priviledge a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ns</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Tax<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> was then pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:64645:58"/> amongſt them. And afterwards when thoſe aforeſaid <hi>Tractatus Illuſtrium</hi> were by the Command of Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> 13. augmented, and by the care of <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcus Zilettus</hi> publiſhed at <hi>Venice</hi> 1584, this <hi>Taxa</hi> was alſo reprinted, and with the reſt dedicated and preſented to the ſaid Pope. And it is worthy our obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, that though the <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> of Rome have placed the <hi>Taxa Cancell: Apoſt:</hi> in their <hi>Expurgatory Index,</hi> yet they except nothing againſt the <hi>Book</hi> printed by the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> but that only which was lately put forth with <hi>Banks</hi> his <hi>Annotations,</hi> or which have been corrupted by <hi>Hereticks:</hi> though it would puzzle the wiſeſt of them to prove any ſuch cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions.</p>
                  <p>Now can any <hi>Romaniſt,</hi> after ſuch full proof, have the impudence to deny that ſuch a Book ever had a being in the World? But what will not a <hi>Papiſt</hi> affirm or deny in his own defence, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of his holy <hi>Mother</hi> the Church?</p>
                  <p>Nay the <hi>Popes</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> have granted <hi>Indulgences</hi> not only for ſins paſt, but alſo for ſinnes to come. Our King <hi>James</hi> proteſts that he had ſeen two <hi>Authentical</hi>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:64645:58"/> 
                     <hi>Bulls</hi> with his own eyes: one when he was very young in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and it was taken from a <hi>Scottiſh Prieſt;</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſaw here in <hi>England,</hi> taken from an <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Medit: upon the L: pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er p:</hi> 584.</note> 
                     <hi>Iriſh-man,</hi> and both of them contain'd a full pardon of all ſins both paſt &amp; to come. And this brings to my remembrance a pleaſant <hi>Story,</hi> which I have often met with: In the time of Pope <hi>Leo</hi> 10 <hi>Tece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> or <hi>Tetzelius</hi> was ſent into <hi>Germany</hi> with a great number of Pardons to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance money for his <hi>Holyneſſe.</hi> This <hi>Pactor</hi> highly commended his <hi>Ware</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he came, and affirm'd that he could pardon all ſins both paſt and to come; whereupon a <hi>German Gentleman</hi> bought ſuch an one of him, and afterwards robb'd the <hi>Pardoner. Tetzolius</hi> was highly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, and threatned him with <hi>Bell, Book,</hi> and <hi>Candle,</hi> but the <hi>Gentleman</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that he bad bought his Pardon for it, declaring that was the ſin he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to commit, when he made that purchaſe: to which the poor <hi>Dominican</hi> could not reply.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect:</hi> 6.</head>
                  <p>BUt perhaps ſome, either through Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty or Covetouſneſſe, may grudge
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:64645:59"/> and grumble to purchaſe their Abſolution at ſo dear a rate: therefore his <hi>Holyneſſe,</hi> to prevent all diſcontent in his children, hath out of his abundant <hi>Charity</hi> and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Authority,</hi> provided for them par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and ſalvation at as eaſie, and lazie a rate as heart can wiſh or deſire. A few <hi>Inſtances</hi> will make this evident. By grant from Pope <hi>John</hi> 20 every bowing of the head (ſaith <hi>Sands)</hi> at the naming of <q>Jeſus, gets twenty yeares Pardon. And to grace that <hi>Ceremony</hi> the more I have heard (ſaith he) ſundry of their famous Divines teach in Pulpit, that Chriſt himſelfe on the Croſſe bowed his head on the right ſide, to reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence his own name which was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten over it.</q> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eur: Spec: p.</hi> 14.</note>
                  </p>
                  <q>The ſaying of the <hi>Beads</hi> over with a <hi>Medal</hi> or other trinket of the <hi>Popes</hi> benediction appendant gets a plenary Indulgence, and delivers what ſoul out of Purgatory one pleaſeth.</q>
                  <p>All the Members of the <hi>Arch-Confra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vid: Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venopened. p.</hi> 15. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3</note> 
                     <hi>of the Sacred Roſary</hi> (and any one may be admitted into it without a penny coſt) are made partaker<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of <hi>Plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences</hi> upon eaſie terms. 1. Upon the day that any <hi>one</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> received into this <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraternity</hi>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:64645:59"/> having confeſſed and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, and recited a third part of the <hi>Roſary,</hi> (all which may be done in a very ſhort time) he gains a plenary Indulgence, and remiſſion of all his ſins. This was granted by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> 5. <hi>Sept:</hi> 27. 1559. 2. Any Member of the <hi>Roſary</hi> in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of death. 1. Being confeſſed, and communicated a plenary Indulgence, granted by the ſame Pope <hi>Sept:</hi> 27. 1559. 2. Or ſaying (with mouth, or in heart) <hi>Jeſus Maria,</hi> a plenary Indulgence. 3. Or calling thrice (either by mouth or in heart) upon the holy name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> a plenary Indulgence, granted by <hi>Pius</hi> 5. <hi>Gregory</hi> 13. <hi>Clement</hi> 8. 4. Or having a bleſſed <hi>Candle</hi> of the <hi>Confraternity</hi> in their hand, in honour of the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> at the time of their departure, a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Indulgence, granted by <hi>Adrian</hi> 6. and confirm'd by <hi>Clement</hi> 7. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Same Auth: p.</hi> 95.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Arch-Confraternity of St.</hi> Francis, called <hi>the Cord of the Paſſion,</hi> are made partakers of the like <hi>Priviledges.</hi> Every one of this <hi>Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> for ſaying the <hi>Crown of our Saviour,</hi> or the <hi>Crown of our Lady,</hi> containing 72 <hi>Paters</hi> and <hi>Aves,</hi> with a <hi>Pater,</hi> and <hi>Ave</hi> for his Holyneſſe, obtains a plenary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:64645:60"/> and remiſſion of all his ſins. Who would deſire pardon and ſalvation upon eaſier terms? I forbear to mention many other <hi>Fraternities,</hi> upon which the <hi>Popes</hi> of Rome have conferr'd the like Indulgences.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bernardine de Buſt:</hi> tells us (as I find <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Anſwer to Jeſ. Chall: p:</hi> 489.</note> him cited by our moſt learned Primate of <hi>Ireland)</hi> that Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> 4. granted an Indulgence of twelve thouſand years for every time that a man in the ſtate of grace (that is, having confeſſed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated) ſhould repeat this ſhort <hi>Orizon</hi> or <hi>ſalutation</hi> of the <hi>Virgin: Hail moſt holy</hi> Mary <hi>the Mother of God, the Queen of heaven, the gate of Paradiſe, the Lady of the world. Thou art a ſingular and pure Virgin: thou didſt conceive Chriſt without ſin: thou didſt bear the Creator and Saviour of the world, in whom I doe not doubt. Deliver me from all evil, and pray for my ſinnes. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And in the Book of the <hi>hours</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin ſecundum uſum Sarum,</hi> we have ſeveral <hi>Prayers,</hi> to which are annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Indulgences for ſeveral thouſand yeares.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To all them that before this Image of pity devoutly ſay</hi> 5 <hi>Pater Noſters, and</hi> 5 <hi>Aves,</hi>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:64645:60"/> 
                     <hi>and a Credo, pitiouſly beholding the Armes of Chriſts Paſſion, are granted thirtie two thouſand ſeven hundred and fifty yeares of pardon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They that deſire to ſee more (and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get the Book) let them peruſe Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet (Papiſtarum Malleus</hi> and <hi>Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his Age,) his <hi>diſcourſe concerning the Idolatry practiſed in the Church of Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And thus I have ſhew'd you how indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent &amp; complying the Principles &amp; practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> are to mens ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral humours, and carnal inclinations.</p>
                  <p>He that underſtands the natural conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of theſe things, cannot wonder that the Church of Rome ſhould have a numerous company of <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> made up of (ſuch as <hi>Davids Army</hi> were) <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam:</hi> 22. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Swearers, Drunkards</hi> &amp;c. looſe and licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious perſons. Nay he may rather won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that all wicked men in the world run not into the <hi>Romiſh Church;</hi> where they may live ſo merrily, and dye ſo ſecurely. Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh</hi> knew what he ſaid, and he ſpake truth when he ſaid it, that were he to chooſe a Religion for licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious liberty, he would chooſe the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Religion. Certainly theres no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:64645:61"/> under Heaven ſo conſonant and congruous to corrupted nature, to fleſh and bloud, as the Religion of the Church of Rome. And thus we have diſpatched the fourth way or Method of Romes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP: VII. <hi>Of Popiſh Signes, and Wonders, and lying Miracles.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>5. WEe come now to diſcourſe of their <hi>feigned Miracles,</hi> by which they have endeavoured (and with great ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſR) to propagate their <hi>Doctrines.</hi> That this ſhould be one of <hi>Antichriſts</hi> Methods to deceive the Nations, and enlarge his Kingdome, is clear from the Apoſtles words 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 2: 8, 9. <hi>And then ſhall that wicked be revealed, whom the Lord ſhall conſume with the Spirit of his month, and ſhall deſtroy with the brightneſſe of his coming: Even him, whoſe coming is after the working of Satan, with all power, and ſignes, and lying wonders.</hi> Where we may obſerve. 1. The time of <hi>Antichriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> coming (for the Papiſts confeſſe that the Apoſtle here ſpeaketh of Antichriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) this was before explicated. 2. The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his coming, which is <hi>after the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:64645:61"/> 
                  <hi>of Satan with all power, and ſignes, and lying wonders;</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (as it is in the Original) <hi>Wonders of falſhood;</hi> not only in reſpect of their <hi>end,</hi> becauſe they tend to confirm errour; but in reſpect of their <hi>forme</hi> too: wanting that which is an eſſential part of Miracles, properly ſo called.</p>
               <p>And that the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> (the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt)</hi> and his <hi>Factors</hi> have uſed this wile and St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atagem to propagate their <hi>Doctrines,</hi> is moſt notorious. As they confidently urge theſe feigned Miracles to prove the Roman Church to be a true Church, ſo to confirm and eſtabliſh their <hi>new coyn'd</hi> Doctrines, viz: <hi>Veneration of Images and ſacred Reliques, Invocation of Saints, Tranſubſtantiation, the Sacrifice of the Maſſe, Purgatory, Papal Indulgences, Prayers for the dead</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The ſecond <hi>Nicent Councel,</hi> which decreed that <hi>Images</hi> ſhould be worſhipped, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth pretty Stories to confirm this Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution. Take one briefly thus: <hi>A certain</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Long: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um: Concil: p:</hi> 389.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſtian leaving an Image of Chriſt behind him in the houſe, from which he re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ved; and a Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſucceeding him, having invited other Jews to dinner, one of them eſpied the Images which the other Jew affirm'd he had not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:64645:62"/> 
                  <hi>before: they ran with great fury and violence upon it, and pierced it in the ſide, out of which iſſued ſuch a ſtream of blood, that they filled a great Water pot with it. Then they reſolved (that they might ſee whether it had any vertue) to ſprinkle ſick perſons therewith; this was done and they preſently recovered.</hi> And in the life of <hi>Damaſcene</hi> we read, that his hand being cut off by the <hi>Saracens</hi> for his profeſſion of the Chriſtian faith, he praying before the <hi>Image</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin Mary,</hi> and ſhewing his hand cut off, fell aſleep, and awaking, found his hand reſtored.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antony</hi> of <hi>Padua,</hi> proved <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation</hi> (to one that deny'd it) by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous teſtimony of his <hi>hungry Beaſt,</hi> before which having ſet <hi>Corn</hi> and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated <hi>Hoaſt, in the name and power of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">* <hi>Chamier Panſtr: Tom</hi> 2. 678.</note> 
                  <hi>thy Creator (ſaith</hi> Antony) <hi>whom I now hold in my hands, I command thee that thou come preſently in an humble manner, and give this hoaſt due reverence. He had no ſooner ſpoken the words, but this devout Beaſt left the Corn, came to</hi> Antony, <hi>bowed the head, and bended the knee.</hi> And leſt one Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle be not ſufficient to confirm you in the belief of ſuch a fundamen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al Article, take one more, in ſhort thus: A Womans
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:64645:62"/> Bees not thriving, by the advice of a Neig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bour, ſhe ſteals a conſecrated <hi>Wafer,</hi> and placeth it in one of her Hives, hoping it would drive away the diſeaſe, and bleſſe their undertakings. The devout Bees, in honour of ſuch a <hi>Gueſt,</hi> fall to work, and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th their honey-Combs make a pretty little Church with windows, a do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, a Belfrey, yea and an Altar too, upon which they laid the Hoaſt, and pay'd great reverence to it. A notable Argument for Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
               <p>If they meet with any that ſcruple their Doctrine concerning <hi>Invocation of Saints,</hi> they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll rubb up their memories and tell them ſome miraculous Stories, to prove <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Martinus Polonus lib:</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 241.</note> it both lawful and profitable. <hi>Leo</hi> 1. <hi>Biſhop of Rome,</hi> being under a ſtrong temptation, and putting forth his hand to kiſſe a Woman, cut it off afterwards. Hereupon being unable to celebrate <hi>Maſſe,</hi> which the people then expected (for it was about <hi>Eaſter)</hi> he became an humble <hi>Suppliant</hi> to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin Mary:</hi> Hereupon ſhe preſently appeared, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ought his hand and reſtored it: and ſo all was well again. And if this miracle be not ſufficient to gain your aſſent to this Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, they have others more miraculous.
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:64645:63"/> They tell us (and we muſt not queſtion the truth of it) that a little <hi>Bird</hi> being ſeized on by a greater, cry'd but out <hi>Ave Maria,</hi> and preſently the great ravenous Bird fell down dead. And that a <hi>Parrat</hi> ſporting her ſelfe out of a <hi>Cage,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing almoſt ſeizd on by an <hi>Hawk,</hi> did but call upon St. <hi>Thomas a Becket,</hi> and the Hawk dyed immediately.</p>
               <p>If any queſtion the power and vertue of the <hi>Sign</hi> of the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> they have innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Miracles, ſome of which they will produce for his ſatisfaction. <hi>Fryar Theobald</hi> (as they tell us) by vertue of the ſign of the Croſſe, walked upon the water over <hi>Tyber. Fryar Andreas de Anania,</hi> who having ſome little <hi>Birds</hi> roaſted at his own deſire to ſtay his <hi>Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite,</hi> yet upon better conſideration, it went againſt his ſtomack todevour them: and being thus reſolv'd, he makes but the <hi>Sign</hi> of the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> and preſently they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, and flew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>way. And St. <hi>Antony</hi> by the Sign of the Croſſe, turned an ugly <hi>Todd</hi> into a fat roaſted <hi>Capon</hi> piping hot.</p>
               <p>If any doubt of the wonderful power <note place="margin">* <hi>Spond: Epit: Anno.</hi> 1172. <hi>p.</hi> 1054.</note> of the <hi>Popes Excommunication; Spondanus</hi> will tell them, that <hi>Dogs</hi> (though never
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:64645:63"/> ſo hungry) would not take bread from thoſe four Knights that murther'd <hi>Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as a Becket,</hi> ſo long as they were under the <hi>Popes Anathema.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that the <hi>Reliques of Saints</hi> are to <note place="margin">† <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>old: L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g: cited. by Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>: tom:</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 679.</note> be honoured, they prove by many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles. A certain <hi>Abbat</hi> deſiring of the <hi>Abbeſſe</hi> of <hi>Col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> the body of one of the eleven thouſand Virgins, promiſed to put it in a golden Box: But not perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his promiſe, when they were at their Mattins (many being preſent, behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and admiring) the <hi>Body</hi> of that <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin</hi> came out of the <hi>Wooden Box</hi> (judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it too mean a lodging place) deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the Altar, paſſed through the Quire, and return'd to her <hi>Companions</hi> at <hi>Colen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you doubt of the immaculate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin Mary</hi> they will tell you that <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> who took much pains to clear up that point, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by her in theſe words <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſcripſiſti Thoma.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will not mention any more of their <hi>New-coyn'd Doctrines,</hi> in confirmation of which many Miracles are produced. Thus doe they endeavour to eſtabliſh their <hi>Novel Doctrines</hi> by lying Wonder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:64645:64"/> Miracles: and great numbers of ignorant and ſuperſtitious perſons have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded by this Method.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Johannes <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentinus</hi> a <hi>Dominican by his Impoſtures in this kind obtained</hi> (Saith <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cath: Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod: Tom:</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 374.</note> Rivet) <hi>a great name in</hi> Bononia <hi>and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded the Magiſtrates and people, that they look't upon him as come down from Heaven: they thought themſelves happy if they could but touch the hemme of his Garment. His Confederates by agreement ſwore that he had raiſed</hi> 18. <hi>perſons from the dead, that he could cure all diſeaſes, and caſt out Devils</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And by theſe Arts, before the cheat was diſcovered, he had got in one year twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thouſand pounds.</hi> And <hi>Tyrrel</hi> the <hi>Prieſt</hi> in his <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> which he drew up in writing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aid, that within the compaſſe of halfe a year in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Raign (when all attempts againſt her ſacred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon were defeated) by their cheating <hi>Exorciſms</hi> they prevailed upon 500, ſome ſay 5000 perſons to embrace the the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That theſe Miracles, which they ſo much boaſt of, are not true, is moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; becauſe the Doctrines which they would confirm by them, are falſe: but God never puts forth his divine power
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:64645:64"/> in working Miracles to eſtabliſh <hi>erroneous Doctrines;</hi> he never ſets his <hi>Seal</hi> to a falſe <hi>Deed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That <hi>Story</hi> of the <hi>Lives</hi> of their Saints, which they call <hi>Legenda aurea,</hi> the golden Legend, is made up of lying prodigies, and prodigious Lyes: So much is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by their own Doctors. <hi>Ludovicus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ives</hi> ſpeaking of it ſaith, <hi>How unworthy both God and men is the Story of the Saints, I ſee no reaſon why it ſhould be called the Golden Legend, being written by one that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De corrupt: Art<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>: lib.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>had an Iron face and leaden heart.</hi> And <hi>Chamier</hi> confirms it by the teſtimony of <hi>Canus: I do not excuſe the Author of that Book intituled Speculum Exemplorum: nor of this Hiſtory, which is called the golden Legend. In that thou maieſt read monſters of Miracles more frequent than true mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; and this was written by one that had neither prudence nor honeſty.</hi> Panſtrat: Cathol: Tom: 2. p. 677. And <hi>Eſpencaeus</hi> ſaith, <hi>that no Stable is ſo full of dung, as their Legends are full of Fables.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In</hi> 1. <hi>Tim: digreſſ: lib:</hi> 1. <hi>p:</hi> 224.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider (as an <hi>Antidote</hi> againſt this tempation) that things may be done (which may ſeem to be real miracles in the judgement of the wiſeſt man on earth) by men of corrupt hearts 7 <hi>Math:</hi> 22, 23.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:64645:65"/> and of corrupt heads 24 <hi>Math:</hi> 24: and therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e we muſt not judge by the Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles what Doctrine is true, but by the Doctrine what Miracles are true. 13 <hi>Deut:</hi> 1—3.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP: VIII. <hi>Of Popiſh Lyes and Slanders.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>6. I Now proceed to the laſt way or method of Romes advancement, or which the Pope and his <hi>Agents</hi> uſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate their <hi>Religion</hi> viz: <hi>impudent lyes and ſlanders</hi> againſt their <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> or who refuſe to ſubmit to the Conduct and government of the Roman Church. This <hi>Method</hi> Rome <hi>Pagan</hi> uſed for the extirpation of <hi>Chriſtianity:</hi> and this <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod</hi> Rome <hi>Chriſtian</hi> hath uſed for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of <hi>Popery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That <hi>Rome Heathen</hi> took this courſe to ſuppreſſe the the growth, yea the being of Chriſtianity, is very clear from <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Hyſtory.</hi> When <hi>Nero</hi> that mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of men, had ſet Rome on fire, which burned nine dayes, to transfer the <hi>Odium</hi> of that impious act upon the Chriſtians, he gave out that they had done it out of malice and revenge. And after wards the Heathen raiſed many malicious ſlanders
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:64645:65"/> againſt them, and laid to their charge moſt horrid crimes; as that they lived in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt: that in their night meetings, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out the Candles, they mixed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a filthy manner: that they killed their Children, and fed upon mans fleſh: that they kept the <hi>Feaſts</hi> of <hi>Thyeſtes,</hi> and committed the inceſt of <hi>Oedipus:</hi> that they were guilty of <hi>Sacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ledge</hi> and <hi>Sedition,</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and worſhipped the head of an <hi>Aſſe.</hi> In <hi>Athens</hi> there was a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurer</hi> which made an <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> that uttered theſe words, <hi>Jupiter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the Chriſtians to be baniſhed out of this City, becauſe they are enemies to him. Harlots</hi> alſo were ſuborned to ſwear that formerly they had been <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and ſo were privie to the wickedneſſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety which they committed amongſt themſelves at their Sabbath-meetings. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid: Tertul: Apol: c.</hi> 7. 9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> Theſe and many more ſuch like calumnies we meet w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th in <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and other <hi>Eccleſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtical Hyſtorians;</hi> by which the hearts of the Common people were ſet againſt <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and the <hi>Emperours</hi> and other inferiour <hi>Governours</hi> incenſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of it. The truth of this appeares by an <hi>Epiſtle</hi> which the Chriſtians in <hi>France</hi> writ to the Brethren
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:64645:66"/> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Phrygia</hi> recorded by <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius: They feigned againſt us</hi> (ſpeaking of the Heathen) <hi>and reported that we uſed feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ: Hyſt lib:</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 1</note> 
                  <hi>of Thyeſtes, and the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt of</hi> Oedipus, <hi>with many other Crimes, which may neither with piety be thought upon, nor with modeſty be uttered, nor without impiety believed: And theſe things being bruited abroad, every body was moved and incenſed againſt us. Then was that ſaying of our Saviours fulfilled</hi> viz: <hi>The time will come, when as every one that ſlayeth you, ſhall thinke that therein he doth God good Service. Then ſuffered the holy Martyrs ſuch torments as no tongue can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe. Great was the rage both of people and Preſidents againſt us</hi> &amp;c. To this I could adde many more proofs out of <hi>Euſebius:</hi> but that is needleſſe.</p>
               <p>And that the <hi>Pope</hi> of Rome and his <hi>Factors</hi> have obſerved the ſame Method to propagate their Doctrines, is moſt noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. How have they loaden with Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies and falſe accuſations the <hi>Enemies</hi> of their Church, eſpecially thoſe of the reformed Religion. They charge <hi>us Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> with <hi>infidelity, cruelty, impiety,</hi> and what not.</p>
               <p n="1">1. With infidelity; that we diſ-believe the Exiſtence of God, the Divinity and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:64645:66"/> Humanity of Chriſt, the immortality of the ſoul, the reſurrection of the dead, and all the Articles of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. With cruelty. How have they ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sands: p.</hi> 98.</note> our proceedings here in <hi>England</hi> againſt their rebellious <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, to the height of <hi>Nero's,</hi> and <hi>Diocleſians</hi> Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, and the <hi>Sufferers</hi> of their ſide in merits of cauſe, in extremity of torments; &amp; in patience &amp; conſtancy to the renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Martyrs</hi> of that hercical age. Of this Subject they have publiſhed a great <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>olume</hi> compiled with great induſtry (many paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages being illuſtrated with pictures) and approved by <hi>Authority;</hi> in ſhort, there's nothing wanting but truth and honeſty.</p>
               <p n="3">3. With impiety; that all manner of <hi>Crimes</hi> are committed and countenanced amongſt us. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith that there are many wicked men among the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> but not one good man among the <hi>Lutheran Hereticks.</hi> Their <hi>Fryars</hi> raiſed and publiſhed many foul ſlanders againſt the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> as that they were <hi>Sorcerers Buggerers</hi> &amp;c. that when they aſſembled together in the night-time, their Paſtors commanded the light<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:64645:67"/> put out, ſaying, <hi>Qui poteſt capere, capiat,</hi> whereupon they committed abominable Inceſts, the Son with his Mother, the Brother with his Siſter, the Father with his daughter &amp;c. They tell the people both in <hi>Pulpit</hi> and private <hi>Conferences,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Sands)</hi> 
                  <q>that the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi> are blaſphemers of God and <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 118. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> all his Saints, that they aboliſh the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments; that they raze or rob Churches, and convert them into Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; that there is no kind of villany which is not currant among them; that in <hi>England</hi> they have neither Churches, nor form of Religion, nor ſerve God any way; that the Engliſh ſince their apoſtacy from the Roman Church are become ſo barbarous, that their Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are very Cannibals, and eat young Children. But upon <hi>Geneva</hi> they are moſt ſevere, affirming that it is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Sanctuary of all impiety, giving entertainment to all the <hi>Rogues, Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> and <hi>Rebels</hi> of other Countries.</q> This was ſo confidently reported in <hi>Italy</hi> (ſaith the fore-cited Author) that ſome <hi>Fryars,</hi> having robbed their <hi>Converts</hi> of their <hi>Church-plate,</hi> and <hi>Repoſitonies,</hi> they brought them in triumph to <hi>Geneva:</hi> but
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:64645:67"/> contrary to their expectation they were forthwith advanced to the <hi>Gibbet</hi> for their labour; which uſage cauſed them to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of their falſe information. And in <hi>Spain</hi> alſo was this report ſo firmly believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that a <hi>Spaniſh Gallant,</hi> who carried a <hi>mint</hi> about him, repaired thither to have ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ps made him for the coyning of <hi>Piſtolets.</hi> Being apprehended, his defence was, that he underſtood their City was free, &amp; gave receipt to all offenders. It was anſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, that they received all offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, but puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their offences. A diſtinction which the grave <hi>Donne</hi> had not heard of before, &amp; the learning of it then coſt him no leſſe than his life.</p>
               <p>And that theſe calumnies might with more eaſe be credited by the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgar,</hi> they confidently report the great <hi>Promoters</hi> of the <hi>Reformation</hi> (as we <hi>Hereticks</hi> call it) <hi>viz: Luther, Calvin, Beza</hi> &amp;c. to be men of looſe <hi>principles</hi> and licentious <hi>practices.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> affirmeth of <hi>Luther,</hi> that <hi>he juſtifies the Arrians,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>they did ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well in expelling the word</hi> (Homouſion) <hi>being a word that his ſoul hated.</hi> Praefat: diſp: de Chriſto. Again, <hi>That faith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be without (even the leaſt) good works, doth not juſtify, and is not faith. Bellar:</hi>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:64645:68"/> de Juſtific: lib: 1. cap. 12. <hi>Luther aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that the ten Commandments belong not to us; for God did not lead us, but the Jewes out of Egypt.</hi> And <hi>how can a man prepare himſelfe to good; ſeeing it is not in his power to make his wayes evil. For God worketh the wicked work of the wicked.</hi> Marqueſſe of <hi>Worceſter.</hi> And concerning his death <hi>Thyraeus</hi> the <hi>Jeſuite</hi> tells us this Storie: <hi>That the ſame day that</hi> Luther <hi>dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there was at</hi> Gheola <hi>a Town in</hi> Brabant <hi>many perſons poſſeſſed of devils, that waited on their St.</hi> Dimna <hi>for deliverance, and were all that day delivered; but the next day they were all poſſeſſed again: whereupon the Exorciſt asked the devils where they had been the day before; and they anſwered, that they were commanded by their Prince to be at the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of their fellow Labourer</hi> Luther. <hi>And for proof of this,</hi> Luthers <hi>own Servant that was with him at his death, looking out at the window, did more then once to his great terror, ſee a company of ugly ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rits leaping and dancing without</hi> &amp;c. De Daemonaicis cap. 8. pag: 16.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Calvin</hi> they charge with theſe blaſphemous paſſages: <hi>That God is the Author of all the evil thats done in the world: That in the death of Chriſt occurs a ſpectacle</hi>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:64645:68"/> 
                  <hi>full of deſperation.</hi> Marq: <hi>That Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaired upon the Croſſe, and was damned.</hi> Bellar: de Chriſti Anima lib: 4. c. 8. And <hi>de Notis Eccleſ:</hi> lib: 4. cap: 17. he ſaith, <hi>that Calvin was eaten up of worms, even as Antiochus, Herod,</hi> and <hi>Maximinus.</hi> And then adds, <hi>that he dyed curſing and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of <hi>Beza</hi> they write that a little before <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sands. p.</hi> 101.</note> his death, he had in full Senate at <hi>Geneva</hi> recanted his Religion, exhorting them, if they had any care to ſave their ſouls, to ſeek reconciliation with the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> and to ſend for ſome <hi>Jeſuites</hi> to inſtruct them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zuinglius</hi> affirms (ſaith the Marqueſſe) <hi>that theſe ſayings, and ſuch like, if thou wilt enter into life, keep the Commandments</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are ſuperfluous, and Hyperbolical: That when we commit adultery, or murther it is the work of God, being the mover, the author or inciter</hi> &amp;c. <hi>God moveth the Thief to kill—he is forced to ſin</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Some of theſe, and many more of the like nature (which I have not time to mention) you may find in the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> of <hi>Worceſters papers</hi> to King <hi>Charles</hi> 1. all which are fully detected by our learned Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> in the ſecond part of his
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:64645:69"/> 
                  <hi>Cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Religioſum.</hi> And thus we have diſpatched the firſt thing propounded; ſhew'd you by what <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Polic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> the <hi>Whore</hi> of <hi>Babylon</hi> hath advanced her ſelf, and deluded the Nations. And who ever conſiders the nature of them, how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariant they are to all Lawes both Divine and humane, and what dreadful menaces are annexed to them in <hi>ſacred Writ,,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doubt of the truth of this <hi>Propoſition</hi> (which was the ſecond thing propounded) <hi>viz: That the wayes and methods which Rome Papal hath uſed to advance her ſelfe, and propagate her Doctrines, will bring inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ruin, and deſtruction upon her.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Some practicall Inferences from the foregoing Diſcourſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ARe theſe the <hi>Wayes</hi> and <hi>Methods</hi> which the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Factors</hi> have uſed to propagate their doctrines?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Here then we may ſee how it comes to paſſe that the Church of Rome hath ſuch a numerous company of <hi>Proſelytes.</hi> There was never <hi>Government</hi> framed by the wit of man more powerful to attain it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſigned ends, than that of Rome; never any either more wiſely contrived, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:64645:69"/> more diligently obſerved; inſomuch that but for the natural weakneſſe of falſhood and diſhoneſty, their external meanes were ſufficient to prevail upon the whole world to ſubmit unto it. Whatſoever either wealth can ſway with the lovers, or voluntary poverty w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th the deſpiſers of the world; what honour with the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious, or obedience with the humble; what great employments with active ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, or perpetual quiet with reſtive bodies; what ſatisfaction the pleaſant nature can take in ſports and paſtimes, or the auſtere mind in diſcipline and rigour; what love either Chaſtity can raiſe in the pure, or voluptuouſneſſe in the diſſolute; what change of vowe; with the raſh, or of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate with the inconſtant; what pardons with the guilty, or ſupplyes with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digent; what Miracles with the Credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and Viſions with the Phantaſtical; what glorious ſhewes with the Vulgar, and multitude of Ceremonies with the ſuperſtitious; in ſhort, whatſoever is congruent and complacential to the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous tempers and diſpoſitions of men, is to be found in the Church of Rome.</p>
               <p>To conclude, never was there a Politie or Government in the world ſo ſtrangely
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:64645:70"/> compacted of infinite contrarieties, all tending to entertain and gratifie the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral humours of men; and by Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence more powerful to attain the ends of its inſtitution.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let us then thankfully acknowledge the infinite goodneſſe and mercy of God in our ſignal deliverances from their <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Conſpiracies,</hi> eſpecially that of this day. I know the Anniverſarie remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance of this eminent <hi>Deliverance</hi> trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> of Rome: they love not to hear of their impious deſignes, when not crowned with ſucceſſe. Some <hi>Romaniſts</hi> would gladly have the world believe it to be a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er cheat, onely a <hi>Trick</hi> of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> then <hi>Secretary</hi> of <hi>State;</hi> and for proofe they very gravely tell us this Storie, <hi>That one lurking under the Council-Table</hi> (and upon what jealouſy came he there?) <hi>conceal'd by the long Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, heard much of the Contrivance.</hi> A <hi>Tal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſo ridiculous, that to endeavour its confutation, would argue one more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, than the <hi>Tale-teller.</hi> If this were a <hi>Cheat,</hi> and known ſo to be, would no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Father Parſons,</hi> and <hi>others</hi> have va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poured w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t all the world over? Would they have concealed ſuch a thing, that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:64645:70"/> would have cleared up their innocency, and caſt ſo much filth and dirt upon us? No man (who ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h ſeen their <hi>Writings)</hi> can imagine that they were ſuch <hi>Friends</hi> to us, and ſuch <hi>Enemies</hi> to their own <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſe</hi> and <hi>Credit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That there really was ſuch a <hi>Plot,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be deny'd till all <hi>Hyſtories</hi> be purged.</p>
               <p>And that it was approved and promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not only by a few inconſiderable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (as others ſuggeſt) is not leſſe evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Sir <hi>William Stanley,</hi> Sir <hi>Edmund Bainham,</hi> Father Parſons Rector of the Engliſh Colledge in Rome, <hi>William B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ldwin</hi> the Leg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Jeſuite in <hi>Flanders, Arhur Crefwell</hi> Legier for their cauſe in <hi>Spain, Hugh Owen</hi> with many others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas were acquainted with this bloody deſign, and highly commended it. Nay ſome of theſe ſolicited the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to have an <hi>Armie</hi> in ready<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe at the water-ſide to waft over into <hi>England,</hi> when notice ſhould be given of that fatal blow.</p>
               <p>In <hi>May</hi> 1605. (the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> having made an <hi>Inſurrection</hi> in <hi>Wales) Father Garnet</hi> writ a letter to the Pope, that a command might come from his <hi>Holyneſſe,</hi> or from <hi>Aquavica</hi> General of the Jeſuits,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:64645:71"/> to prevent all commotions of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks here in <hi>England,</hi> that we might be lull'd aſleep by their diſſembled quietneſſe and conformity. This requeſt was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; though his other <hi>viz:</hi> to have it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd upon <hi>Cenſures,</hi> was deny'd, leaſt it might be an impediment to that grand deſign. Peruſe the <hi>Relation</hi> of the whole proceedings againſt thoſe barbarous <hi>Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> where you will find all this, and much more confeſſed by them.</p>
               <p>Again, that the <hi>Pope</hi> was privie to this <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Andrews Reſponſ: ad Apol: Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm: c.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Plot,</hi> and approved of it, is clear from the voluntary Confeſſion of a Jeſuite, who affirm'd, that three <hi>Bulls</hi> were ſent from <hi>Rome</hi> upon this occaſion; and ſhould have been publiſhed in three of the chiefeſt places of <hi>England,</hi> had their deſign ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded: but that failing, they were ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt.</p>
               <p>That the remembrance of this great deliverance may more affect us, let us conſider it with all its adjuncts and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. We ſay that in <hi>Morals,</hi> the <hi>Circumſtance</hi> is more then the <hi>ſubſtance:</hi> So many times in <hi>deliverances,</hi> the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncts may be more than the <hi>matter.</hi> The cutting of a Stone may be more precious than the ſtone it ſelfe; and the ſtamp and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:64645:71"/> workmanſhip of more value than the Metal. I cannot ſay ſo here; but doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe theſe two Adjuncts <hi>viz: freeneſſe</hi> and <hi>fulneſſe,</hi> doe adde much to the glory of it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Obſerve how freely we were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the bloody complotments of our <hi>Roman Adverſaries.</hi> Many ſignal deliverances hath God wrought for his Church in former Ages, but was there ever any ſo free as this? God delivered his Church from the barbarous conſpiracy of <hi>Haman:</hi> but what prayers, and teares, and faſtings did it coſt <hi>Eſther,</hi> and <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai,</hi> and the Jewes ere they could ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it? 4 <hi>Eſth:</hi> 16. But this deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance came not upon the <hi>wings of our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> but Gods <hi>free mercy;</hi> we were ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of our danger, and therefore could not make Deliverance the Subject of our prayers. <hi>Maſſes</hi> were ſaid in <hi>Rome</hi> for the good ſucceſſe of the <hi>Catholick Deſign,</hi> but no prayers were made in <hi>England</hi> for our deliverance from it: and yet deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. In a word, <hi>we were delivered, before we ſought deliverance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Obſerve how fully we were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. The <hi>Plot</hi> was laid for a full de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, to cut off the <hi>King, Queen,</hi> and their hopeful <hi>Iſſue,</hi> our honourable
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:64645:72"/> 
                  <hi>Nobility,</hi> our reverend <hi>Clergies,</hi> our grave and learned <hi>Judges,</hi> the flower of our <hi>Gentry,</hi> yea the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi> No <hi>Countrie,</hi> nor <hi>Age</hi> ever brought forth ſuch a <hi>Monſter</hi> of <hi>Treaſon;</hi> ſaith <hi>Thuanus,</hi> ſpeaking of the <hi>Powder-Plot. Hiſtor:</hi> lib: 135. p. 1215. No ſtroke ſo mortal as that of a <hi>Thunder-bolt,</hi> no hatred ſo cruel as that which fetcheth its pretences from Heaven. The loſſe of a particular perſon is oft-times, but like the putting out of a <hi>Candle,</hi> which brings onely darkneſſe to a roome: but the ruine of a <hi>State,</hi> is like the <hi>Eclipſe</hi> of the Sunne, which brings a detriment to the whole <hi>Hemiſphere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And obſerve how fully God defeated their bloody deſign: there was not the leaſt hurt done. This deliverance was like that of the three Children in the fiery furnace 3 <hi>Dan:</hi> 27, <hi>There was not ſo much as an hair of their head ſinged, neither were their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oats changed, nor the ſmell of fire had paſſed on them.</hi> Or like that of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> from the fury of <hi>Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cherib,</hi> who coming up againſt that City full of pride and rage, intended nothing leſſe than the utter ruine and deſtruction of it: but faith God, <hi>he ſhall not ſhoot an arrow there.</hi> Even thus were we delivered.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:64645:72"/>
               <p> O let us be for ever thankful for this free and full, this eminent and glorious deliverance! not only verbally, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally; with our <hi>lips,</hi> and in our <hi>lives.</hi> It is obſervable that the Iſraelites gracious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance out of <hi>Egypt</hi> is made the <hi>Preface</hi> to the ten Commandments. Holyneſſe of life is the life of thankfulneſſe.</p>
               <p>How apt we are to fail in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this duty is too evident both from ſacred <hi>Writ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and daily <hi>experience.</hi> How did Gods own people abuſe ſignal and tranſcendent mercies? not only by entertaining low and mean thoughts of them, but even by ſinning againſt the Author of them. Can there be a greater wickedneſſe, than for a <hi>Penſioner</hi> of the <hi>Court</hi> who receives an ample <hi>Stipend</hi> from the <hi>King,</hi> to lay it out in buying poiſon to deſtroy him, or in raiſing, rebellion to dethrone him? And what is it that ſuch men doe leſſe, who abuſe the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God to the ſervice of their luſts: and turn them, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did the <hi>Jewels</hi> of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> which God had given them, into a curſed <hi>Idol,</hi> before which bow'd and worſhipped?</p>
               <p>Such a foul ſin it is, that it were to be wiſhed, that no example could ever be
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:64645:73" rendition="simple:additions"/> produced of it; or that it had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd to the generations that are long ſince paſt: that <hi>Jeſurun</hi> had been the laſt, that <hi>waxed fat and kicked.</hi> 32 <hi>Deut.</hi> 15. or that the <hi>Prophet</hi> had made the laſt complaint, that Gods <hi>Corne,</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> and <hi>Oyle,</hi> and <hi>Silver,</hi> and <hi>Gold</hi> were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in the Service of <hi>Baal. Hiſ:</hi> 2. 8. But alas its a ſin that lives to this day; a ſin that <hi>England</hi> is deeply guilty of. If we compare this <hi>Land</hi> with other <hi>Nations</hi> and <hi>Churches,</hi> we ſhall find our Portion to be like that of the Firſt born, double to what any of our Brethren in other Kingdomes have enjoyed. What bleſſing is it, that deſerves to be ſtiled <hi>matchleſſe, tranſcendent, glorious,</hi> which God hath not conferr'd upon us? If Peace be it, we have had it; if Plenty, we have had it; if Victory, we have had it; if the Goſpel, we have have had it. Our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable <hi>Enemies</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> have attempted all wayes, that <hi>wit</hi> or <hi>malice</hi> could invent, to deprive us of what is, and ought to be moſt dear unto us, and bring upon us the heavy <hi>Yoke</hi> of <hi>Popiſh Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions,</hi> which neither we, nor our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were able to bear.</p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:64645:73"/>
               <p> If curſing could have done it, what a miſerable and forlorn People had we been at this day? How often hath <hi>Balack</hi> ſent to <hi>Balaam,</hi> come curſe <hi>Iſrael,</hi> come defy <hi>England?</hi> and how often hath that <hi>Balaam</hi> curſed our <hi>Iſrael.</hi> We have heard of his <hi>Anniverſarie Anathema's,</hi> wherein this <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> have been ſtruck with the thunder and lightning of his Papal curſe. <hi>But the curſe cauſleſſe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) ſhall not come.</hi> And we may ſay to <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> did to <hi>Iſrael</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Balaams</hi> curſe. <hi>Deut:</hi> 23. 5. <hi>Nevertheleſſe, the Lord thy God would not hearken unto</hi> Balaam: <hi>but the Lord thy God turned the curſe into a bleſſing unto thee, becauſe the Lord thy God loved thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if <hi>power</hi> and <hi>policy</hi> could have done it, we had been a wretched and ruin'd people long ago; witneſſe the <hi>Spaniſh Armado,</hi> and the <hi>Gun-powder-Plot. Theſe Archers</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> have ſorely grieved us, and ſhot at us, and hated us. But our Bow hath abode in ſtrength, and the arms of our hands have been made ſtrong, by the hands of the mighty God of <hi>Jacob. Gen:</hi> 49: 23, 24.</p>
               <p>O but how ſadly have we abuſed theſe ſignal mercies and deliverances! How is
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:64645:74"/> that mercy of mercies ſleighted by us, nay a burden to us, which ſhould be priz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above all the endearments of this world, I mean, the <hi>Goſpel of ſalvation?</hi> How have we waſted theſe mercies, as the <hi>Prodigal</hi> did his Portion, upon our luſts and filthineſſe? we have ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then'd our hands by them in rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Author</hi> of them. Not onely the banks of <hi>Religion,</hi> but <hi>Cavility</hi> too are broken down. Whereas 'tis uſually ſaid, that ill manners produce good lawes, we have reverſt the Aphoriſme, and the good precepts of our Religion have introduced the moſt corrupt manners. Our holy Faith which, like a foundation ſhould ſupport good works, hath like a Gulfe ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them up. And ſo univerſal a depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is there amongſt us, that we have ſcorce any thing left to diſtinguiſh us from the moſt barbarous people, but a better <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ame</hi> and worſe <hi>vices.</hi> How many give no other demonſtration of their belief of a Deity, than their Oaths and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? and in ſtead of calling unto mercy to ſave them, their ordinary prayer is, God damne them. How many think it a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iece of gallantry to ſcoffe at Religion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oll upon God, and make ſport with his
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:64645:74"/> lawes? In aword, how many think it an argument of judgment to be above the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of Conſcience, and the height of courage to defy Heaven, and outdare the Almighty? O tell it not in <hi>Gath,</hi> nor publiſh it in the ſtreets of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kelon,</hi> that a people, whom God hath ſo ſignally own'd, and miraculouſly delivered, ſhould thus requite the Lord.</p>
               <p>How juſtly may we expect ſome remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable judgments as the product of theſe monſtrous impieties? and that if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that ſins againſt mercy are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt a darling attribute of God, which of all others he moſt delights to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal, and make known to the Sons of men, Now the more any ſin is injurious to this attribute of mercy, the more black it muſt needs be. No darkneſſe is more formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, than that of an Eclipſe, which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults the very <hi>Veſſels</hi> of light; no taſte more unſavory, than that of ſweet things, when corrupted: even ſo no ſinne more hideous, than that which would darken the brightneſſe of Gods love, and corrupt the ſweetneſſe of his mercy; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore none more provoking to wrath and jealouſie.</p>
               <p>To conclude, let us not frantickly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:64645:75"/> that omnipotency, which we are not able to reſiſt, nor deſpiſe that goodneſſe which is our only refuge: but ſince it hath pleaſed God in wrath to remember mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, let us tranſcribe his Copy, and be as kinde to our ſelves, as he hath been to us. O that we may take pattern from <hi>Niniveh, cry,</hi> and <hi>cry mightily unto God,</hi> joyn humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation to our prayers, and reformation to both. And could we be perſwaded to doe this with the ſame <hi>ſincerity</hi> and <hi>univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> we might hope with the ſame <hi>ſucceſſe.</hi> Would all who have brought their fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands, bring alſo their teares, it might ſecure us ſuch a tranquility here, as may calmly convoy us to that impaſſible ſtate, <hi>where all teares ſhall be wiped from our eyes.</hi> And ſo much for the ſecond Inference.</p>
               <p>3. Think not then of an accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> It hath been the deſire of many, and the endeavour of ſome to work a reconciliation betwixt our <hi>Church</hi> and that of <hi>Rome:</hi> theſe have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted an impoſſibility. No communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between light and darkneſſe, truth and falſhood, Chriſt and Antichriſt. The North and South Poles may ſooner meet, than an accommodation with the Church of Rome be effected. Come out of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:64645:75"/> is the voice from Heaven; come out in affection, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd come out in perſon: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate far from them. Say with <hi>Jacob</hi> Gen: 49. 6, 7. <hi>O my ſoul come not thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their ſecret: unto their aſſembly, mine honour, be not thou united. Curſed be their</hi> Principles <hi>for they are</hi> Damnable, <hi>and their</hi> Practices <hi>for they are</hi> cruel.</p>
               <p>4. Much leſſe then think of returning to <hi>Rome.</hi> Stand faſt in that truly <hi>Ancient, Catholick,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick Faith,</hi> which you have received. This <hi>Exhortation</hi> cannot be adjudg'd unneceſſarie, if we conſider that <hi>Romes Factors,</hi> the great <hi>Whores Panders</hi> are crafty and ſubtile to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce men to their Religion. See how the Spirit of God deſcribes them, 9 <hi>Rev:</hi> 1, 2. &amp;c. The Papiſts confeſſe that here by the <hi>Starre</hi> fallen from heaven is meant the <hi>Maſter</hi> of ſome error and hereſie, and by the <hi>Locuſts</hi> that ariſe out of the earth, the <hi>Teachers</hi> of theſe hereſies.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Starre</hi> (ſaith our learned <hi>King James</hi> in his <hi>Paraphraſe</hi> on <hi>Revel:)</hi> is the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome:</hi> and the <hi>Locuſts</hi> that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the aire, are <hi>Monks, Fryars, Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> &amp;c. They have <hi>Crowns of gold, the the faces of men, and hair like Women:</hi> all al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luring, enticing, and tempting. And that
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:64645:76"/> you may ſtand faſt in the truth, and not be ſeduced to <hi>Popery,</hi> I wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> commend to you (paſſing by many others) theſe two directions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Doe not nouriſh any known ſin. The <hi>Jewel</hi> of faith can never be kept in a crack'd <hi>Cabinet,</hi> a crazy Conſcience He who puts away a good conſcience, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning faith will ſoon make ſhipwrack. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 1. 19. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ophane Goſpellers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a prey to thoſe that goe abirding for ſouls with their corrupt Doctrines. 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 2. 10, 11. The Apoſtle here deſcribes the perſons that ſhall be ſeduced by <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt:</hi> they are ſuch as walk after their luſts, and will not receive the love of the truth. Theſe like the out-ſetting <hi>Deer</hi> are ſhot, while they within the <hi>Pale</hi> are ſafe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Read the Scriptures carefully and conſtantly. It was the Speech of a dying <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> of this place to his <hi>Chaplain, that in all the word of God, he could not find the leaſt ground for Poperie.</hi> And ſo much, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y more is confeſſed by certain <hi>Biſhops</hi> in <hi>Bononia</hi> in their <hi>Letter</hi> of Advice to the <hi>Pope</hi> concerning the eſtabliſhment of the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>pag:</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Roman Church: Laſtly (which amongſt the counſels and directions given to your Holyneſſe at this time, is chiefeſt and moſt weighty)</hi>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:64645:76"/> 
                  <hi>the greateſt care and diligence muſt be uſed, that as little of the Goſpel as may be (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgar Tongue) be read in theſe Cities which are within your Dominions. Let that little ſuffice, which is wont to be read in the Maſſe: and more than that let no mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal be allow'd to read. For ſo long as men were content with that little, your affairs ſucceeded according to deſire; but quite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwaies ſince ſo much of the Scriptures was publickly read. In ſhort this is the Book, which above all others, hath raiſed theſe ſtorms and tempeſts. And truly, if any one read that Book</hi> viz: the Scriptures, <hi>and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the cuſtomes &amp; pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſes of our Church, will ſee that there is no agreement betwixt them, and that the Doctrine which we preach is altogether different from, and ſometimes contrary to that contained in the Bible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Letter or Epiſtle was firſt diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by <hi>Vergerius,</hi> after the death of Pope <hi>Paulus</hi> 3. ſaith <hi>Craſhaw:</hi> and <hi>Wolfius</hi> gives us a large account of it, Lection: Memorab: Tom: 2. p. 549.</p>
               <p>Carefully and conſcientiouſly obſerve theſe <hi>directions,</hi> and I doubt not but you will be preſerved from, or enabled to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome all temptations to <hi>Popery.</hi> I
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:64645:77"/> will conclude with one of the <hi>Collects</hi> appointed for this day.</p>
               <p>O <hi>LORD, Who didſt this day diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cover the ſnares of death that were ſaid for us, and didſt wonderfully deliver us from the ſame; Be thou ſtill our mighty Protector, and ſcatter our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that delight in blood. Infatuate and defeat their counſels, abate their pride, aſſwage their malice, and confound their devices. Strengthen the hands of our gracious King</hi> Charles, <hi>and all that are put in authority under him, with judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and juſtice, to cut off all ſuch work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of iniquity, as turn religion into re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and faith into faction; that then may never prevail againſt us, or triumph in the ruine of thy Church among us: But that our gracious Soveraign and his Realmes, being preſerved in thy true Religion, and by thy mercifull goodneſſe protected in the ſame, we may all duly ſerve thée, and give thee thanks in thy holy Congregation, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
